<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A looking-glasse for malignants: or, Gods hand against God-haters. Containing a most terrible yet true relation of the many most fearefull personall examples (in these present times, since the yeere, 1640.) of Gods most evident and immediate wrath against our malevolent malignants. Together with a caveat for cowards and unworthy (either timorous or treacherous) newters. Collected for Gods honour, and the ungodlies horrour, by John Vicars. Imprimatur hic liber. Iohn White.</title>
            <author>Vicars, John, 1579 or 80-1652.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 129 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95890</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V317</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E33_18</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19020</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860543</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860543</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112665</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95890)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112665)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 6:E33[18])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A looking-glasse for malignants: or, Gods hand against God-haters. Containing a most terrible yet true relation of the many most fearefull personall examples (in these present times, since the yeere, 1640.) of Gods most evident and immediate wrath against our malevolent malignants. Together with a caveat for cowards and unworthy (either timorous or treacherous) newters. Collected for Gods honour, and the ungodlies horrour, by John Vicars. Imprimatur hic liber. Iohn White.</title>
                  <author>Vicars, John, 1579 or 80-1652.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 38, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Iohn Rothwell, at the signe of the Sunne in Pauls church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a blank preliminary leaf.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "feb: 19th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>God --  Wrath --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112665:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A
LOOKING-GLASSE
FOR
MALIGNANTS:
OR,
Gods hand againſt God-haters. CONTAINING
A moſt terrible yet true relation of the many
moſt fearefull perſonall examples (in theſe preſent
times, ſince the yeere, 1640.) of Gods moſt evident and
immediate wrath againſt our malevolent Malignants. Together with a Caveat for Cowards and unworthy
(either timorous or treacherous) Newters. COLLECTED
<hi>For Gods honour, and the ungodlies horrour,</hi>
BY
JOHN VICARS.</p>
            <bibl>Pſalm. 120. 3, 4.</bibl>
            <q>What ſhall be given, or done unto thee thou falſe tongue? even ſharpe
Arrowes with hot coales of Iuniper.</q>
            <bibl>Jerem. 18. 18.</bibl>
            <q>Then ſaid they (Iſraels malignants) come, and let us deviſe devices a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
Jeremiah; come and let us ſmite him with the tongue, and let
us not give heed to any of his words.</q>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>Imprimatur hic Liber</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Iohn White.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed for <hi>Iohn Rothwell,</hi> at the ſigne of the Sunne in Pauls
Church-yard. 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:112665:2"/>
            <head>TO THE
RIGHT HONOURABLE
Sir IOHN WOLLASTONE,
Knight; Lord Major of the renowned
City of LONDON:
AND
To the Right Honourable and truly
elect Lady, the Lady WOLLASTONE, his
moſt vertuous and truly pious Conſort; J. V. moſt humbly and heartily prayeth all
encreaſe of Honour here, and the bleſſed aſſurance
of Heaven hereafter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our owne ſingular, and even Connative
<hi>Candor, piety,</hi> and <hi>courteſie</hi> to <hi>All;</hi> and
many and moſt <hi>immerited favours,</hi> deepely
and duely ingaging <hi>Me</hi> to both your <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,</hi>
have induced, yea compelled me to
be ever moſt ſtudious of bounden <hi>Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</hi>
I therefore (with that honeſt poore
<hi>Countrey man,</hi> of whom I have read, who
ſeeing many <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Nobles</hi> preſenting
to their <hi>Emperour</hi> very rich and rare <hi>Preſents; He</hi> alſo to ſhew his
love, brought onely his <hi>owne Picture</hi> painted, and holding forth in
his hand the figure of a faire and rich <hi>Iewell,</hi> with this Motto over
it, <hi>Et hoc vellem:</hi> That is, <hi>And I would give ſuch a Iewell as this is,
were I able.</hi> So I (I ſay) having no better a <hi>preſent</hi> (as yet) to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb facs="tcp:112665:3"/>
to your <hi>Honours,</hi> have moſt humbly made bold to dedicate to
both your <hi>Honours</hi> (together with my <hi>devoted ſelfe</hi>) this plaine
yet uſefull <hi>Looking-glaſſe.</hi> VVhich though it be but of a homely
dreſſe, yet will repreſent to your <hi>Honours</hi> variety of remarkable
objects, touching the miſerable <hi>Malignants</hi> and <hi>Anti-Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians</hi>
of theſe our times; moſt worthy (I beleeve) your <hi>Honours</hi>
ſerious view and favourable acceptance. And to whom, indeed,
may I more fitly tender ſuch a tender and fragil piece or <hi>utenſill,</hi>
as a <hi>Looking-Glaſſe</hi> is, then to your good <hi>Honours,</hi> whom both I
and this whole City, yea I may ſay, the whole Kingdome doe
know by moſt happy experience (witneſſe your good <hi>Lordſhips</hi>
moſt pious, prudent, and vertuous <hi>Government</hi> of this famous City,
and witneſſe alſo your good <hi>Ladyſhips Maſculine vertues,</hi> as ſo
many precious <hi>Pearles</hi> treaſured up in a <hi>Feminine Cabinet,</hi> I meane
a moſt <hi>heroicall holy Heart,</hi> together with the conſtancie and loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty
of both your <hi>Honours</hi> to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> in the <hi>Parliaments
Cauſe;</hi> and whom therefore (I ſay) I know <hi>moſt willing</hi> to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
and uſe this my <hi>Looking-Glaſſe, Candidâ manu,</hi> with candid
and courteous <hi>Acceptation,</hi> and alſo <hi>moſt able</hi> to patronage and
protect it, <hi>A rapacibus &amp; furioſis malignantium unguibus,</hi> from the
uncivill and defiling fingers of any of all our unreaſonable male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volent
<hi>Malignants.</hi> Goe on therefore, my good Lord (as moſt
honourably you do, guarded and guided by the wiſdom and power
of <hi>Gods holy Spirit,</hi> and ſupported by the daily prayers of <hi>Gods
Saints and Servants</hi>) to countenance and encourage <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> and
to diſcountenance and keepe under the enemies of <hi>Godlineſſe, Peace</hi>
and <hi>Truth,</hi> even as your <hi>Honours</hi> late moſt worthy <hi>Predeceſſour</hi>
did, to Gods glory and his everlaſting honour; ever ſetting before
your <hi>Honours</hi> eyes, and having in your bleſſed <hi>Breſt</hi> that <hi>heart-for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying-promiſe</hi>
and admirable incouragement given by God himſelf
to his faithfull ſervant <hi>Joſuah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſuah 1. 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>As I was with my ſervant Moſes, ſo
will I be with thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13 5.</note> 
               <hi>I will not faile thee nor forſake thee. Be ſtrong
therefore and of a good courage.</hi> VVhich that your <hi>good Lordſhip</hi> moſt
holily and happily may be, is and ever ſhall be the dayly prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your good Honours moſt humbly devoted,
JOHN VICARS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:112665:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it is too frequently and familiarly knowne (<hi>bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volent</hi>
or <hi>malevolent</hi> Reader, whoever thou art)
that to the hearing of Gods Word there come as well
<hi>eares of ſcorne</hi> as <hi>eares of corne:</hi> So, I make no
doubt but this my <hi>Looking-Glaſſe</hi> ſhall meet <hi>eyes
of enmity</hi> and <hi>hearts of rancour,</hi> as it ſhall of
<hi>Amicability</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian Candor.</hi> However, being careleſſe of
the <hi>malignity</hi> of the <hi>one,</hi> and moſt ſtudious of the <hi>benignity</hi> of the
<hi>other,</hi> I here invite thee to the view thereof; wherein thou ſhalt ſee
repreſented to thine <hi>eyes</hi> and <hi>underſtanding, various, ſerious,</hi> and <hi>ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
objects,</hi> fit for them both to contemplate, ruminate, and feed
upon. <hi>Variety,</hi> I ſay, of <hi>evidences</hi> and <hi>examples</hi> of Gods moſt juſt
and immediate indignation <hi>againſt</hi> and <hi>upon</hi> the unnaturall, malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
and even beſtiall <hi>Malignants</hi> of theſe times (for ſo ſayes the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 49. 12.</note> 
               <hi>That even the moſt honourable of men wanting hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly
wiſdome and underſtanding, are compared to beaſts that
periſh.</hi> And well were it with them too, were they but as bad as beaſts
and had not <hi>immortall ſoules,</hi> as ſome <hi>Mad-braines</hi> of late have moſt
falſly, fooliſhly, and blaſphemouſly gone about to prove and prate of)
who impiouſly fret and fight againſt <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Cauſe.</hi> Together with
our ſilly and ſottiſh <hi>Newters</hi> and uncomfortable <hi>Cowards,</hi> who time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly
or treacherouſly deſert and forſake their <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>Parliaments
Cauſe,</hi> which unqueſtionably is <hi>Gods.</hi> By all which ſad and ſerious
<hi>Examples</hi> (for, as our old Axiome is, <hi>Examples move more, and
are more prevalent than Precepts</hi>) my maine and onely aime is to
endeavour (by Gods aſſiſtance, for the Chriſtian love I beare to their
ſoules eſpecially) to ſhew them the <hi>errours</hi> and <hi>evils</hi> of their <hi>courſes</hi>
and <hi>carriages</hi> therein, and (if it be poſſible) to worke and win them
<pb facs="tcp:112665:4"/>
to a true and timely retractation for the good of their <hi>ſoules</hi> and <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi>
both here and hereafter.</p>
            <p>But whereas,<note place="margin">Object.</note> it may be, our <hi>Malignants</hi> will here object, either cut
of <hi>incredulity,</hi> or <hi>malignancy,</hi> or both, that all theſe fearfull <hi>exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi>
here alleaged, are but <hi>Chimaera's,</hi> and falſe or fictious <hi>Bug-bears</hi>
to ſcare children or fools, and therefore they the leſſe regard them.</p>
            <p>All that I will anſwer hereunto is this,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> That I profeſſe (as in the
preſence of God) I have uſed all <hi>care</hi> and <hi>diligence</hi> to ſearch and be
aſſured of <hi>the truth of them all,</hi> and am able to produce very able and
honeſt <hi>teſtimonies</hi> of them, beſides what I have expreſſed with the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples</hi>
themſelves. If therefore our unhappy and hood-winkt <hi>Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants,</hi>
through their owne <hi>flinty obſtinacy,</hi> or <hi>benummed ignorance</hi>
and <hi>incredulity</hi> (whereby <hi>etiamſi perſuaſeris, non perſuadebis,</hi>
Though you make things ever ſo cleare, yet they will not be convinced)
will not ſuffer theſe things to worke ſo kindely on their Conſciences as is
herein <hi>deſired</hi> and <hi>indeavoured;</hi> yet then I am confidently perſwaded
(by Gods gracious aſſiſtance) they may produce <hi>this threefold iſſue
and effect.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1.</note> Firſt, they may be a meanes to confirme and ſtrengthen the
faithfull and faſt friends of the Parliament in their godly and well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded
reſolution and Chriſtian courage to perſevere therein.<note place="margin">2.</note> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
to reduce and reforme ſome (at leaſt) of the more moderate, tender,
and fearfull-ſpirited ones.<note place="margin">3.</note> And thirdly, they muſt needs ſerve for the
greater condemnation of our deſperate <hi>Malignants,</hi> and to leave them
(thereby) utterly inexcuſable, if ſtill they perſiſt in their perverſe and
froward obduracie. But what ever be the iſſue, <hi>Liberari egomet ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam
meam.</hi> I have, ſo far, diſcharged my duty, and will yet farther
unfainedly pray, that the Lord may thereby get ſome glory, though by
ſo weake and unworthy an inſtrument, as is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord,
JOHN VICARS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112665:4"/>
            <head>A
LOOKING-GLASSE
FOR
MALIGNANTS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat there hath been in all ages from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
of the World,<note place="margin">A naturall An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipathy in the wicked againſt the godly.</note> even ever ſince that grand
enmity which God put between the <hi>Womans</hi>
and the <hi>Serpents</hi> ſeed, a naturall <hi>Antipathie</hi> and
<hi>inveterate malignity</hi> in the <hi>wicked of the World</hi>
againſt the <hi>godly,</hi> is undeniable and moſt cleare
both in ſacred, prophane, and morall Hiſtories.
And that this <hi>connative malignity</hi> in them hath in all places and
times broken out into moſt deadly feud and pernicious <hi>Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>
both by <hi>Hand</hi> and <hi>Tongue,</hi> eſpecially, is as cleare and conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuouſly
apparent to all that have their eyes in their heads and will
ſee, or underſtanding in their hearts, and not be wilfully blind and
obſtinately hard-hearted.<note place="margin">Gods hand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Truth-Traducers.</note> And that God alſo, hath evermore moſt
evidently and eminently manifeſted his high indignation, and even
immediate wrath and diſpleaſure, eſpecially on <hi>Tongue-perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi>
of his precious people, and on blaſphemous <hi>Traducers</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmearers
of his immaculate <hi>Truth,</hi> all times and places can produce
moſt copious preſidents and moſt ſad examples.</p>
            <p>To paſſe by and pretermit all <hi>by-paſt preſidents</hi> and former feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
examples of Gods immediate and revengefull hand on ſuch
<hi>malignant Delinquents</hi> in former ages, and extant (I ſay) in ſacred
Scriptures and other Hiſtories, and not to inſiſt on that moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable
one in <hi>Gods booke,</hi> though moſt punctually pertinent to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:112665:5"/>
our purpoſe,<note place="margin">2 Kings 2. 23, 24.</note> of above <hi>forty children</hi> ſlaine by <hi>two wild Beares</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately
upon their mocking the godly Prophet of the Lord, and
onely calling him <hi>Bald pate</hi> in ſcorne and deriſion; juſt as our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants
and their children jeeringly and ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffingly call Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
now adaies by that fooliſh &amp; non-ſence name of <hi>Round-heads.</hi> To
paſſe by this, I ſay, and all other of ancient or more moderne times,
and to come briefly and roundly (ſince they will have it ſo) to our
owne times, even ſince the moſt unhappy breaking out of theſe
moſt unnaturall and inteſtine bloody broyles within our Kingdom
of <hi>England;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>England</hi> not empty of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Gods wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Tongue-perſecuters of Truth.</note> wherein God hath not left us empty (in Chriſtian
ſorrow be it mentioned) of many moſt evident demonſtrations of
his juſtly incenſed indignation againſt the <hi>malignant Heart and
Tongue-perſecuters</hi> of our times (againſt whom I mainely intend
this Treatiſe) but hath given us as many and as memorable ſad
ſpectacles of his apparent diſpleaſure, in his ſcoffing enemies ruine,
ſorrow and ſhame, as ever any former age or Nation ſaw and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved;
which being ſo freſh and fully knowne among us, even
many of us yet ſurviving, they may moſt juſtly ſerve (as I conceive)
both as occaſions of griefe and godly ſorrow in Gods Saints to ſee
theſe <hi>miſerable malignants,</hi> who forſooth pretend and boaſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
as brave <hi>Proteſtants</hi> as the beſt, yet to be ſo Godleſſe and
graceleſſe, ſo bitingly and bitterly to flout and affront the <hi>Lord
Chriſt</hi> himſelfe in his <hi>holy members,</hi> and in his moſt <hi>glorious cauſe;</hi>
and alſo of moſt juſt ſhame and bluſhing at leaſt (if not of heart-breaking
and bleeding converſion) in them all to ſee ſo dangerous
and deſperately dying conditions of their malicious and malevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<hi>brethren in iniquity;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Optimum eſt alienâ ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ui iaſaniâ.</note> and thereby either to learne (and indeed
it is a ſpeciall piece of wiſdome <hi>to learne to be wiſe by other mens
miſeries</hi>) to feare God and doe no more ſo ſinfully, or elſe moſt
certainely and infallibly to feare and looke for like wrath and ruine,
ſooner or latter, in one kind or other, if not I ſay prevented by true
and timely repentance.</p>
            <p>Now in the proſecution of this Treatiſe,<note place="margin">A threefold modell of the Mirrour or Looking-glaſſe.</note> and in the framing and
forming of this our intended terrour ſtriking <hi>Looking glaſſe,</hi> I
ſhall by Gods aſſiſtance, with all convenient brevity and hiſtoricall
fidelity, endeavour to ſhew and ſet forth theſe three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall herein repreſent and ſet forth unto the fight of our
<hi>mole-ey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Malignants,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Gods hand againſt malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants and their cauſe.</note> (if, at leaſt, they will not too peeviſhly and
perverſly ſhut up their eyes againſt moſt cleare and radiantly <hi>Sunne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112665:5"/>
Truths) Gods moſt evident and eminent hand againſt our male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volent
malignants, and their moſt accurſed cauſe;</hi> in divers remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<hi>generall</hi> pieces and paſſages of <hi>Gods admirable providence, croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
and curbing their moſt wicked courſes</hi> and <hi>contrivements</hi> againſt
<hi>God,</hi> in our <hi>Parliament</hi> and their juſt proceedings; and then alſo in
ſome <hi>particular</hi> neerer and cloſer <hi>perſonall</hi> and peculiar demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
of theſe cleare Truths.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſhall moſt conſpicuouſly and apparently perſonate
and ſhew unto them <hi>Gods moſt heavy hand upon malignants,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Gods moſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy hand upon malignants perſons.</note> in many
moſt immediate and fearefully inflicted judgements and <hi>perſonall
puniſhments,</hi> ſuddenly and ſorely laid upon them, even in the very
<hi>acting</hi> of their <hi>malignancy;</hi> whereby they muſt needs with <hi>Pharao's</hi>
malignant <hi>Magicians</hi> cry out and confeſſe, <hi>Digitus Dei,</hi> certainly,
this was no leſſe then the <hi>very hand of God upon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly and laſtly, I ſhall herein exhibite to the eyes and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,
both of <hi>Malignants,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. A Caveat to Cowardly and faint-hearted Neuters.</note> and alſo of all <hi>cold</hi> and <hi>cowardly
Neutrals,</hi> and of either <hi>falſe</hi> or <hi>faint-hearted deſerters</hi> of the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
cauſe,</hi> and alſo of all unſetled and unreſolved weake Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
in foure or five moſt <hi>memorable,</hi> and (as I may ſay) <hi>Tragae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comicall
examples</hi> of Gods <hi>juſtice</hi> mixt with <hi>mercy,</hi> in juſtly woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
yet graciouſly healing the conſciences of ſome ſuch as had
either <hi>wilfully</hi> or <hi>weakely</hi> deſerted the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and therein
<hi>Gods unqueſtionable cauſe,</hi> even the <hi>worke</hi> of a moſt glorious, pure,
and pious <hi>Reformation</hi> of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi> And ſo I ſhall ſhut
up this our <hi>Looking-glaſſe</hi> with a briefe hortatory concluſion to
all ſorts of men and women both <hi>malignant</hi> and <hi>benevolent</hi> or <hi>wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here now I might in the firſt place, rubbe up our <hi>malignants</hi>
dull memories,<note place="margin">1. Gods hand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants.</note> (and that not impertinently) and rouze up their
drouſie eye-lids, and dead hearts, with the review and remembrance
of that moſt remarkable and memorable paſſage of Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
how in the beginning of theſe moſt uncivill Civill-warres
and commotions among us,<note place="margin">1. Gods hand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants in the ſtrange beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of the ſouldiers in the firſt Army into the North a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Scots.</note> when by the prevalent power of the
<hi>malignant Parricides</hi> on the Kings part, an Army was firſt raiſed to
goe into the <hi>North</hi> againſt our honeſt and harmleſſe brethren of
<hi>Scotland,</hi> and that the Souldiers then preſſed and provoked to goe
forth to fight againſt them, in their march thither-ward (though
they themſelves were but prophane fellowes, rude and irreligious
young men, and therefore one would have thought, moſt fit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112665:6"/>
to promote ſuch an irreligious worke and warre as that
was,) how ſtrangely the Lord over ruled their hearts and ordered
their ſpirits, making them to divert and turne all the edge of their
ſury and diſaffection againſt the <hi>Malignant cauſe</hi> and <hi>quarrell,</hi> and
upon the <hi>malignant</hi> and <hi>popiſh</hi> party themſelves that had ſet them
on worke, over-turning their Altars in all Churches and Chappels
whereſoever they came and found them breaking in pieces and
burning the railes about them, plundering and terretying the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous
<hi>Baals-prieſts,</hi> and <hi>popiſh ſonnes of Belial</hi> whereſoever they
found any of them; and not onely refuſing to be led and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
by <hi>popiſh</hi> Captaines and Commanders, but flying in their
faces, and killing and wounding divers of them, Which <hi>hand of
God againſt them,</hi> in the very ſame kind, hath been alſo admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
ſeconded now againe lately in thoſe 800 or 1000 Souldiers
brought out of <hi>Ireland,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Gods-hand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, in the Souldiers ſent out of <hi>Ireland</hi> (ſince the Ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of armes there) to fight againſt the Parliament.</note> ſince that accurſed <hi>ceſſation</hi> of Armes there,
and landed at <hi>Bristol;</hi> intended for that traiterous parricide Sir
<hi>Ralph Hopton,</hi> to fight againſt our moſt pious <hi>Parliament:</hi> But, I
ſay, how admirably the Lord turned their hearts ſuddenly, from
that moſt accurſed <hi>cauſe,</hi> and how that upon the tender of an <hi>oath</hi>
unto them to fight againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> they utterly refuſed it,
flew in the faces of their Commanders, and made them fly away,
vowing and proteſting with apparent expreſſions of great indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
that they would not fight for the <hi>popiſh</hi> party in <hi>England,</hi> (as
they had not in <hi>Ireland</hi>) and thereupon joyntly reſolved to force
their way (as they moſt faithfully did) from <hi>Briſtol</hi> (where they
were firſt landed) to <hi>Bathe,</hi> &amp; ſo to <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> to fight on the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi>
ſide, under the command of that ever moſt highly to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured
commander Colonell <hi>Maſſie,</hi> who gave them moſt free
and friendly entertainment.<note place="margin">3. Alſo in the Weſterne and Northern parts of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their ſeeming ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe there.</note> To which I might here moſt perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently
and pregnantly adde the yet more late defection of very
many of their intended party both in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> to <hi>Lime, Poole,</hi> and
<hi>Plimouth,</hi> even then when they had beene ready armed for <hi>Hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi>
ſervice in the <hi>South.</hi> In the <hi>North</hi> alſo divers both of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try
and Commons who have deſerted <hi>New caſtle;</hi> and in <hi>Wales</hi> and
<hi>Cheſhire</hi> alſo (now later, I ſay) of the <hi>Engliſh-Iriſh</hi> Souldiers, who
would by no means fight againſt the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
               <note place="margin">4. In many me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable plots alſo admirably diſcovered, and croſſed.</note> Together with the
detection and diſcovery of many moſt miſchievous <hi>plots</hi> and <hi>baſe
deſignes</hi> of <hi>treachery</hi> moſt admirably and ſtrangely diſcovered, and ſo
happily and timely fruſtrated, even by the immediate mercy and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112665:6"/>
good hand of God; as that moſt bloody <hi>Plot</hi> againſt the <hi>Parliament,
Jan.</hi> 4. 1641. The Plot of the <hi>Scots</hi> Army at their former com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
in among us, to have beene ſent againſt the <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>City</hi>
of <hi>London.</hi> The late Plot againſt <hi>Hull</hi> by Sir <hi>Iohn Hotham</hi> and
his ſonne. And the ſeverall moſt dangerous <hi>Plots</hi> (under pretence
of <hi>Treaties for peace,</hi> forſooth) againſt the moſt renowned and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
City of <hi>London,</hi> as that dangerous Plot by <hi>Waller, Challe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,
Tomkins, &amp;c.</hi> And that more lately now of Sir <hi>Bazil Bro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k,
<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iolet</hi> (or rather <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>arlet</hi>) and hypocriticall <hi>Riley;</hi> with very many
other of theſe kindes almoſt all over the whole Kingdome, all too
well knowne, and too tedious here to relate, and which I have
moſt fully and particularly related in my <hi>Parliamentary Chronicle,</hi>
intituled, <hi>God in the Mount.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together alſo with the Lords moſt admirable diſcountenancing,
yea curſing and blaſting all the wicked deſignes in the Kings party
ever ſince that hideous and helliſh ceſſation of Armes in <hi>Ireland,</hi>
with thoſe moſt <hi>barbarous</hi> bloody and damnable <hi>Iriſh Rogues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">5. In Gods moſt juſtly diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing and making odious even to Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that horrid ceſſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Armes in Ireland.</note>
which was moſt impiouſly plotted by the wicked malignant Coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cellors
on the Kings ſide, for their (falſly) hoped mighty advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
in the advancement of their <hi>bloody cauſe;</hi> but which hath (by
Gods marvellous wiſdome, mercy, and good providence) proved
one of the moſt <hi>ominous,</hi> and <hi>eminently</hi> odious meanes of the ruina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
and overthrowing of their moſt <hi>accurſed cauſe</hi> and wicked
<hi>courſes,</hi> even their <hi>malignants</hi> themſelves being judges; and which
our good God hath clearly ratified, I ſay againe, by the extreme
<hi>ill ſucceſſe</hi> they have had ever ſince in all their wicked undertakings;
and contrariwiſe,<note place="margin">6. And their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme ill ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe ever ſince.</note> in the great and <hi>good ſucceſſe</hi> our God hath given
to us ever ſince, eſpecially ever ſince our moſt holy and happy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring
into a <hi>Covenant</hi> with our God, and <hi>bleſſed League</hi> with our
honeſt and religious <hi>Brethren</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi>
               <note place="margin">7. Our good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe ever ſince the Covenant with Scotland.</note> witneſſe our happy vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories
in <hi>Lincolnſhire, York<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhire, Lime, Poole, Plimouth, Newport-Pannell,
Aulton, Grafton-Houſe, Bewley-Houſe, Holts-Houſe,</hi> and
<hi>Arundell-Caſtle,</hi> with others; in which places, ſome reckon the
Enemy hath loſt (beſides exceeding much Armes and Ammuniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
and beſides the brave and <hi>rich ſhip</hi> taken at <hi>Arundell-Caſtle,</hi>
a moſt admirable providence) betweene three and foure thouſand,<note place="margin">8. The admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble breaking out of the Swedes againſt Denmarke.</note>
but we may juſtly reckon a farre greater number. Beſides, the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable
providence of God in ſtirring up (beſide the whole Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of our loyall brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi>) the whole Kingdome of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112665:7"/>
               <hi>Swethland,</hi> to fall furiouſly and fortunately on the Kingdome of
<hi>Denmarke,</hi> a moſt admirable providentiall piece, mightily to croſſe
and curbe our <hi>Engliſh Malignants</hi> hopes and deſignes againſt us.
But to come more <hi>particularly</hi> and <hi>perſonally</hi> neere to our intended
purpoſe in this firſt branch of our <hi>Looking-glaſſe of Gods hand
againſt our Malignants;</hi> eſpecially, I ſay, becauſe perſonall <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularities</hi>
come neerer and cloſer then <hi>generalities.</hi> I ſhall here
therefore inſtance firſt in the ſtrange <hi>hand of God perſonally manifeſted
againſt them,</hi> in that moſt admirable overture and alteration of the
courſe of things to the ſhame and ſorrow of our unluckey Lordly
Prelates, to live to ſee their voluptuous princely Palaces (as Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter
houſe and Ely houſe) turned into priſons, but eſpecially
the ſpacious and ſpecious palace of that <hi>Arch-adverſary</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi>
and his <hi>Cauſe</hi> among us, that <hi>grand Ringleader</hi> and accurſed <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triver</hi>
of all theſe our preſent miſchiefes and miſeries (next to our
ſinnes) yea, the very <hi>head</hi> and <hi>heart</hi> of <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>Laick-Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants</hi>
(according to their owne <hi>Popiſh</hi> diſtinction) I meane the
<hi>Arch-Prelate of Canterbury,</hi> on whom it moſt neerly and cloſely
fell out by divine providence, ſo (ſtrangely and even admirably)
ordering it.<note place="margin">9. Gods hand againſt Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Laighton</hi> made maſter Lambeth houſe, now converted from a Palace to a Priſon.</note> Namely, that that honeſt and religious Gentleman,
Doctor <hi>Laighton,</hi> that great and grievous <hi>Sufferer</hi> for the <hi>cauſe</hi> of
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> under the cruell tyranny of that foreſaid <hi>popiſh Perſecuter,</hi>
ſhould not onely live to ſee himſelfe delivered out of the ſnare, but
his old <hi>grand Adverſary</hi> himſelfe to come into it in his ſtead; and
that the ſaid <hi>Arch-Prelate</hi> ſhould be faſt lockt up as a traiterous
priſoner in the <hi>Tower of London,</hi> whiles this good Doctor is made
<hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter</hi> of the <hi>Prelates</hi> Palace at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> and this ſaid
pompous or rather <hi>popiſh palace,</hi> where ſo many precious Saints
and ſervants of the Lord had beene moſt wickedly arraigned and
condemned to priſon, ſhould now be turned into a priſon, to lock
up moſt looſe and prophane <hi>Malignants;</hi> a moſt ſtrange and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable
<hi>hand of God</hi> certainly <hi>againſt them.</hi> Yea, and I might here
againe remember them of that moſt remarkable overture of things
among us in theſe later times; namely, how it moſt admirably
pleaſed the Lord to bring it ſo to paſſe by his <hi>all overpowring hand
of providence,</hi> that the <hi>Arch-Prelate</hi> of <hi>Canterbury</hi> being impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> as an <hi>Arch-Traitor</hi> to our <hi>Church</hi> and
<hi>State;</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhould be pleaſed to cauſe the ſaid <hi>Arch-Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates</hi>
lodgings in the Tower to be ſearched for dangerous &amp; traiter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112665:7"/>
Papers, Books, and VVritings, and who muſt be the man
fixed on for the performance of this ſervice, but that moſt famous
and faithfull,<note place="margin">10. Gods hand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>William Prynnes,</hi> (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly a great ſufferer by the Arch Prelate of Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) being ſent to ſearch the ſaid Arch-Prelates lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Tower.</note> pious and patient <hi>Saint</hi> and <hi>Sufferer</hi> for <hi>Chriſt</hi> and
his <hi>Cauſe,</hi> Maſter <hi>William Prynne;</hi> who coming into the ſaid <hi>Arch-Prelates</hi>
bed-chamber betimes in the morning, with a guard of
Souldiers to ſecure the buſineſſe, and approaching the <hi>Prelates</hi>
bedſide before he was u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Prelate</hi> asked him, who he was:
This precious and ſweet Gentleman anſwered, my name is <hi>Prynne;</hi>
VVhat, ſayes the <hi>Prelate,</hi> are you he that ſuffered? Yea, ſayes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<hi>Prynne,</hi> I am he whom you moſt unjuſtly and injuriouſly perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted.
Juſt as good <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſaid to his <hi>brethren,</hi> at the time of his
diſcovering and making himſelfe knowne unto them, <hi>I am Joſeph
whom ye ſold into Egypt.</hi> O what a ſtab to the heart ſhould this have
bin to this <hi>perſecuting Prelate</hi> at that word (<hi>I am that Prynne whom
you cauſed ſo grievo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſly and ſo unjuſtly to ſuffer</hi>) had not his heart bin
more hard &amp; ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mantine then a nether mil-ſtone,<note place="margin">Gen. 45. 4.</note> and moſt extrem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
cauterized, yea, ſtigmatized with the hotteſt iron of moſt deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
impenitency! and that then Maſter <hi>Prynne</hi> proceeding to the
due execution of the charge and truſt repoſed in him by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,
ſhould (<hi>juſtiſſimâ illâ coeleſti Lege-Talionis</hi>) moſt juſtly,<note place="margin">Juſtiſſima coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtis Lex-Tali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis.</note> I
ſay, ſearch the Pockets of the <hi>Prelates</hi> wearing clothes, before he
would ſuffer him to put them on and riſe out of his bed, directly
as he and ſome of his <hi>popiſhly</hi> affected Confederates had formerly
dealt with ſome moſt eminent Members of a <hi>Parliam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt</hi> formerly
diſſolved, and as he had cauſed Maſter <hi>Prynnes</hi> owne Chamber and
Study, and many others alſo to be often moſt violently broken
into and ſearched, to the deeply indangering of their precious
lives (which undoubtedly he greedily hunted after) if it might
have beene,<note place="margin">As was done to reverend Maſter <hi>Henry Burtons</hi> houſe and ſtudy.</note> but therein (praiſed be the Lord) God gave this
<hi>curſt Cow</hi> (according to the Proverbe) or rather raging fat <hi>Bull
of Baſhan,</hi> ſhort hornes; the Lords good providence and their
owne innocence happily preventing this bloody deſigne of theirs.
And might not here now this <hi>Arch-Prelate</hi> on the ſerious conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration
of theſe Premiſes, in juſt remorſe of Conſcience, have
cryed out againſt himſelfe (like that heatheniſh King <hi>Adonibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeck,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judges 17.</note>
had he not had, as I toucht before, a more then heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh,
obdurate, and impenitent heart) <hi>Thus and thus have I done to
others, and now am I thus juſtly ſerved by them;</hi> onely with this
difference, That I am uſed farre more mercifully then I uſed
them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:112665:8"/>
I might here alſo adde and copiouſly commemorate unto our
<hi>mole-eyed Malignants</hi> Gods admirable providence in ſo ſtrangely
ordering and diſpoſing of things by <hi>this preſent</hi> moſt memorable
<hi>Parliament;</hi>
               <note place="margin">11. Gods hand againſt the Malignant party in the Trienniall Parliament.</note> not onely to contrive a moſt free and ſpontaneous
or voluntary conſent of all the <hi>three Eſtates</hi> in <hi>Parliament</hi> to the
ſetling of a <hi>Trienniall Parliament</hi> for the future rectifying of
things amiſſe in Church and State, and the more prudent and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident
moderation and government of all ſorts of State-affairs;
but alſo, I ſay, that both <hi>King, Peers,</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> even <hi>both
Houſes of Parliament,</hi> with his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> ſhould ſo admirably and
unanimouſly make it indiſſoluble, and (but by the ſword, like
<hi>Alexanders Gordian knot,</hi> which now the Kings <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſticall</hi>
Army is impiouſly, and (I truſt) fruitleſly labouring to do)
irrevocable <hi>Act,</hi> That <hi>this preſent Parliament</hi> ſhould not bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved
nor broken up,<note place="margin">12. And eſpecially in a perpetua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> but by the joynt and unanimous conſent of
<hi>both Houſes of Peers and Commons.</hi> Which <hi>Act</hi> of theirs (as it
were) perpetuating <hi>this Parliament,</hi> by (I ſay) a moſt ſtrange pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence
of God, what a moſt admirable <hi>Block</hi> it hath laid in all
the wicked <hi>wayes</hi> of that viperous generation of <hi>Atheiſts, Papiſts,</hi>
and <hi>Malignants,</hi> mightily thwarting, croſſing, and cruſhing their
moſt deſperate and deepeſt deſignes? I am not able (I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge)
to expreſſe it, and onely Time is able to make it manifeſt,
to the glory of God, and wonder-ſtriking aſtoniſhment in the
hearts of both <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Bad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though in the laſt, yet not in leaſt place, I might here put
our Malignants in remembrance (for they are, as we all ſee, too
willing to forget and ſlight both <hi>Gods hand againſt them,</hi> and his
<hi>great mercies towards us</hi>) how by meanes of this preſent moſt pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<hi>Parliament,</hi>
               <note place="margin">13. Gods hand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants cauſe in Church-government and matters of Religion.</note> 
               <hi>Gods hand hath beene moſt admirably bent againſt
them</hi> and their moſt impious Cauſe, both in the <hi>expulſion,</hi> and (I
truſt in the Lord) utter <hi>extirpation</hi> of that moſt <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> and
tyrannicall <hi>Hierarchie of popiſh Prelates</hi> (and that moſt eſpecially by
their owne proud practiſes and deſperate deſignes even againſt the
Parliament it ſelfe, witneſſe their Petition to the King that ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
their ſitting in Parliament) <hi>Arminian Doctors,</hi> and moſt ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous
<hi>Prieſts,</hi> thoſe <hi>ſonnes of Belial,</hi> all over the Kingdome:
And alſo in their ſteads, the moſt holy and happy <hi>reduction</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration</hi>
of our baniſhed and abuſed, faithfull, painfull, and pious
Paſtors, <hi>even after Gods owne heart;</hi> together thereby with the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112665:8"/>
bleſſed injoyment of pure and powerfull Ordinances, and that in
admirable plenty and freedome, as the like was never ſeene in this
Kingdome. Beſides, the rare and long deſired and now happily
effected ruine and razing downe of <hi>popiſh</hi> high places among us,
never (ſince the firſt Reformation) till now taken away; in defacing
and deſtroying <hi>popiſh Images, Organs, Croſſes, Crucifixes,</hi> and ſuch
like abominable and Idolatrous, ſuperſtitious, Popiſh, apiſh Trinkets
both in Churches and elſewhere; eſpecially the ruinating of that
moſt infamous and moſt abominable <hi>Romiſh</hi> Monument of idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try
<hi>Cheap-ſide Croſſe,</hi> in the very heart of <hi>London,</hi> and burning abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
of thoſe baſe and beggarly <hi>Romiſh Reliques,</hi> even in the very
ſame place where that <hi>accurſed Croſſe</hi> had with a Whores forehead
bin ſo long advanced among us; and (which is the ſum of all our
juſt admiration in all forementioned) all theſe things done ſo ſoon,
and in ſo ſpeedy a ſpace as within the compaſſe of two or three
yeares at the moſt: Moſt admirable demonſtrations (I ſhould
thinke) <hi>of Gods hand unqueſtionably thus ſeene and ſet againſt
them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And might not then <hi>All theſe;</hi> yea, <hi>any one of theſe</hi> premiſed
preſidents <hi>of Gods moſt immediate hand againſt them,</hi> moſt juſtly
ſerve to even wreſt open the wilfully ſhut up, and blinded eyes of
our Malignants? Sure, me thinkes, they ſhould, ſave that 'tis great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to be feared they are given up to a reprobate ſenſe, if they ſtill
perſiſt in ſuch unheard of, and moſt ſtrangely <hi>marbled obſtinacy.</hi>
But yet ſince they may peradventure in their accuſtomed hardneſſe
of heart be little or nothing moved or prickt in Conſcience with
theſe ſo pregnant preſidents and cleare demonſtrations of <hi>Gods vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicative
hand againſt them.</hi> Yet, I ſay, we will come yet more cloſe
upon them, and give them yet more home and heavy <hi>perſonall
ſtrokes</hi> of <hi>Gods</hi> juſt wrath and <hi>revenging hand,</hi> not onely <hi>againſt
them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Gods hand upon Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants perſons.</note> but <hi>upon them,</hi> even, immediately on the very act of their
moſt impious and blaſphemous words and wicked miſcarriages to
and againſt the ſaints and ſervants of the Lord, making good his
owne everlaſting and unperiſhing Word by the Prophet (marke it,<note place="margin">Eſay 26. 11.</note>
I beſeech you, O all yee moſt deſperately minded and wilfully
blinded <hi>Malignants,</hi> as a word of rouſing errour unto you)
<hi>Lord, when thy hand is lifted up againſt them, they will not ſee; but
they ſhall ſee and be aſhamed for their envy at thy people;</hi>
               <note place="margin">A momento for Malignants</note> 
               <hi>yea, the fire
(of rage) of thine enemies ſhall divour themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="examples">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:112665:9"/>
               <head>Examples.</head>
               <p>The firſt fearfull example (then) of <hi>Gods</hi> moſt juſt <hi>vindicative
hand</hi> and avenging indignation, even moſt evidently falling heavy
by a ſore and heart-piercing <hi>perſonall blow</hi> upon the outragious
maligners, and graceleſſe and godleſſe inveterate haters of the wayes
of Piety, and truly and thorowly intended <hi>Reformation of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
ſhall be this:</p>
               <p>One <hi>Charles Roſe</hi> (a Roſe of a very unſavory ſent) an Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
to one Maſter <hi>Charnell</hi> a Carver of VVood,<note place="margin">Gods hand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of London as a juſt caveat to all malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant London Apprentices.</note> at the upper end of
<hi>Fanchurch-ſtreet</hi> neere <hi>Algate</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> who put himſelfe into the
Parliaments ſervice a little after <hi>Bartholomew tide</hi> 1642. pretending
to be willing to ſide with the <hi>Parliament</hi> againſt the <hi>common enemy,</hi>
but ſecretly intended and reſolved when he ſhould finde a faire op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity
(as he told his fellow-ſervant) to joyne with the <hi>King</hi>
and his Army againſt the <hi>Parliament:</hi> And when he was to goe
forth, declared further (in the hearing of his Miſtreſſe) <hi>That he
was now going to helpe to make halters to hang the Round-heads.</hi> And
it was obſerved by his Maſter, in his former carriage, That he was
of a refractory, yet diſſembling ſpirit; and thus he marching forth
with a baſe treacherous heart to the <hi>cauſe of God</hi> and the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
was ſuddenly ſtricken by the juſt hand of God on the way,
ſometimes ill and ſometimes well, and being at laſt in his march
as farre as into Buckinghamſhire in the way to <hi>Alisbury,</hi> he was
ſuddenly and fearfully ſtricken mad and utterly diſtracted &amp; bereft
of his ſenſes. Now three of my very loving and religious friends
travelling into thoſe parts, found this wretched young man in the
high way as they rode, and ſaw him one of the ſaddeſt ſpectacles
that ever they beheld, for he was ſtarke naked, onely a courſe old
ſackcloth throwne over his ſhoulder, neither Hat on his head,
nor Shoes on his feet, his eyes very red with weeping, and ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
and ſtaring as one affrighted; ſo theſe my friends came to him,
asked him whither he was going, and whence he came, but hee
would give them no anſwer, nor take any reliefe in money (which
they proffered him) but fell downe and cryed out, <hi>Oh my Soule, my
Soule;</hi> whereupon they all three ſtayed ſtill, alighted from their
horſes, and with much adoe, at laſt got him to the next Towne,
and by the way he was heard to ſay, <hi>Blood, Blood.</hi> It pleaſed God
to direct theſe my friends to an Inne in the Towne, where the
Hoſteſſe of the houſe, on knowledge of his name, knew his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112665:9"/>
where theſe my good friends tooke ſome care to have him
lookt unto, and ſome of the Towne tooke care after their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
to have him conveyed to his Father, who lived ſome 16. or 18.
miles from that place about <hi>Oxford.</hi> When his Father ſaw him,
he churliſhly refuſed to give him any entertainment (which, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe,
was inhumanely and unnaturally done) yet herein obſerve
the righteous hand of God too, who as he hath promiſed, that
<hi>when a mans wayes pleaſe him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 16. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>he will make even his enemies to be at
peace with him;</hi> So likewiſe (by the juſt law of contraries) when
our wayes, wits, and parts are <hi>againſt God</hi> and <hi>goodneſſe,</hi> he will make
even our beſt friends to be at enmity with us. For, as here, his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
I ſay, utterly rejected him, and ſuddenly diſpatched him to
<hi>London</hi> to his Maſter, where he lived a while after pitifully diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted,
and never recovered his ſenſes againe; but about three houres
before his death, he ſeemed to have ſome reaſonable apprehenſion
of things, and to be ſomewhat ſenſible, and juſt then was heard to
cry out bitterly, <hi>He was a dogge, he was a damned wretch,</hi> and thus
miſerably died. And the truth of all theſe paſſages, ſince my three
honeſt and religious friends left him, they had from his Maſter
and Miſtreſſe, upon their farther enquiry after him. O that this
ſad and fearfull example of this ſo ſure and ſevere <hi>hand of God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
this malignant young man,</hi> might be as terrible to our <hi>London
malignant Apprentices,</hi> yea, and their <hi>malignant Maſters</hi> too, as
that affrighting <hi>hand-writing</hi> on the wall was to that wicked <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhazar,</hi>
to make them tremble and quake, and to make them heare
and feare, and doe no more ſo wickedly.</p>
               <p>In the time of the ſiege of <hi>Hull</hi> in <hi>Yorkeſhire,</hi> in the yeere of the
Lord 1641.<note place="margin">2. A Maſter Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, at the ſiege of <hi>Hull</hi> ſmitten dead upon his fearfull curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſhoot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off of a Piece of Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</note> among many other very memorable and remarkeable
paſſages in that famous ſiege this was one, which I have by moſt
credible and indubitable information from thence, That the Kings
Cormorants having ſtraitly begirt that ſtrong Town by land and
by water alſo, and they having planted three pieces of Ordnance at
a point of the river called <hi>Haſſell,</hi> to hinder any paſſage of Barkes
and Veſſels from comming into <hi>Hull,</hi> and a Keele comming laden
in the River toward the Towne, the Maſter Gunner ſhot at her, and
miſt her, whereupon being (it ſeems) inraged, he ſwore, <hi>God damne
him, if he did not ſinke her at the next ſhot:</hi> And preſently charging
a Piece as he thought fit, and furiouſly diſcharging it, the Piece
brake in pieces, and inſtantly killed the Maſter Gunner himſelfe,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112665:10"/>
and ſome two or three others that ſtood neere unto him; but the
Barke or Veſſell paſſed ſafely into <hi>Hull,</hi> without any prejudice or
hurt. A moſt fearefull example to terrifie (I ſhould thinke, if it
might be) ſuch execrable curſing and ſwearing <hi>Malignants.</hi> The
truth whereof was (I ſay) confirmed by moſt credible teſtimony
from <hi>Hull,</hi> immediately after this accident <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> out.</p>
               <p>In the yeere alſo 1642. ſome of Prince <hi>Ruperts</hi> Forces facing and
aſſaulting <hi>Windſor-Caſtle,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3. A Captaine in Prince <hi>Ruperts</hi> Army at <hi>Eaton</hi> neer <hi>Windſore</hi> fearfully ſlaine as he was fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly curſing</note> and making many ſhots at it, but ſtill
miſſing what they aimed at, it being a little aime, and ſo not eaſily
hit, a Captaine amongſt them (but his name my honeſt Intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer
knew not) from <hi>Eaton,</hi> where they had made their <hi>Station,</hi>
cryed out to the Gunner, who was going to fire a Drake againſt
the Caſtle, <hi>Give me thy Gun-ſtocke, for, God damne me (ſayes this
wretch alſo) I will ſlay ſome of thoſe Round-head Dogs;</hi> and while
the <hi>Oath</hi> or <hi>cauſleſſe Curſe</hi> was yet warme in his mouth, ere hee
could fire the Piece, a ſhot from the Caſtle daſht him in the face,
brake his teeth into his throat, of the paine and ſmart whereof he
lay lingring in much miſery for two or three dayes, and then died
in a miſerable and wretched condition. This relation I had from
a very honeſt Gentleman (then a Souldier and Officer in <hi>Windſore-Caſtle</hi>)
and my very good friend and acquaintance, whoſe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
I know to be without exception.</p>
               <p>About Aprill 23. 1643. being the Lords Day, one Maſter <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi>
Vicar of <hi>Sheriff-Hales,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">4. A malignant Miniſter in the midſt of his Sermon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Round-Heads, ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fearfully ſmitten dumb.</note> preaching upon a portion of Scripture
out of the 120. Pſalme, tooke occaſion thence in his Sermon to
vent bitter imprecations againſt <hi>Round-heads</hi> (that is, Gods faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
ſervants, and the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Parliaments</hi> loyall and faſteſt
friends) charging them with Faction, Rebellion, and ſuch like
opprobrious ſcandals, adding withall, in expreſſe termes, That
the <hi>Powder-plot,</hi> and other Treaſons that have beene practiſed by
<hi>Papiſts,</hi> were nothing to this late <hi>Round-new-invention</hi> of the
<hi>Round-heads.</hi> At which words (having ſtood hardly halfe his
time) he moſt ſtrangely on a ſudden gaſped and gaped as he ſtood
in the Pulpit, and ſtared in the Auditors faces, but could not ſpeak
a word more for a good ſpace after, the people all that while, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
amazed at this ſo ſudden and moſt ſtrange a dumbe-ſhew in
him. At length he ſtooping downe, as it were to take up ſome
what at his feet, re-erected himſelfe, and then ſaid, Let us give
thankes for what we have heard, which he accordingly did, in a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:112665:10"/>
ſumbling and hardly intelligible manner<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſoone made an end,
and ſo went home; but what became of him ſince I have not
heard.</p>
               <p>Alſo in the pariſh of <hi>Hollowell</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> one of the inhabitants
of the ſaid pariſh being a moſt licentious and prophane fellow, ſet up
a May-pole in the Summer-time, 1641. and that it might tranſcend
the vanities and impieties of other May-poles,<note place="margin">5. Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked fellow at Oxford in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up a May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pole with a Roundhead on it, and ſhooting at it.</note> ſet upon this the
picture of a man in a Tub, thereby (as he ſaid) to deſcribe a <hi>Round-head;</hi>
which picture, as it was credibly reported, he made in deriſion
of a godly Gentleman, a Munciple of one of the Colledges in <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford;</hi>
and the reaſon why it muſt repreſent this Gentleman, was,
becauſe he was truely religious and uſed repetition of Sermons,
ſinging of Pſalmes, and other holy duties in his houſe. This pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture
being thus ſet up on the May-pole, the ſaid prophane fellow
the authour of it, with his looſe and licentious companions, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
themſelves mad-merry about it, at laſt muſt needs goe ſhoot
at the <hi>Round-head</hi> upon it, and having for this purpoſe brought
Muskets with them and other pieces, one of them, being the ſervant
of the <hi>chiefe maſter</hi> of this wicked <hi>May-game,</hi> ſhot and did hit the
Picture; at which the ſaid Maſter fell a laughing extreamly, and on
a ſudden ſunke downe, falling into a ſharpe and terrible convulſion
fit, and ſo continued a long time after very ſicke, and in great paine
and miſery; but whether he be ſince alive or dead, I am uncertaine.
This relation I had confirmed to me by an honeſt young Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
a Scholler of <hi>Oxford,</hi> then reſident in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and an eye-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
of moſt of it, beſides other credible information.</p>
               <p>In the ſame City of <hi>Oxford</hi> alſo, a company of prophane fellows
and deepe drinkers met together in a Taverne, and being (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the
cuſtome is) mad-merry,<note place="margin">6. Gods hand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing healths to the confuſion of the Round-heads in a Taverne.</note> in the midſt of their cups would needs goe
drinke a health to the confesſion of Round heads, which having ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly
gone round, one among the reſt not content therewith
(being, it ſhould ſeem, too ſoundly whitled with his carouſed cups)
would needs for joy (forſooth) of this health thus drunke, riſe up
and dance, and cut a caper, uſing theſe or ſuch like words, <hi>Come</hi>
(ſaies he) <hi>I will now cut a caper to the confuſion of Round-heads;</hi>
but he beginning to dance and cut his caper, his head it ſeemes,
being too light to rule his heeles, ſuddenly fell downe and broke
his legge, whereof (being carried home) he lay in great paine and
miſery, and not long after died thereof; this alſo confirmed by cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112665:11"/>
teſtimony, In the time of the ſiege of <hi>Redding</hi> by the right
honourable the Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> the <hi>Parliaments</hi> moſt renowned <hi>Lord
Generall,</hi> there hapned (as is well knowne) a moſt notable and
remarkable skirmiſh between ſome of our Parliaments forces, and
the Kings Cormorants from <hi>Oxford,</hi> at a place called <hi>Canſam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi>
In which fight moſt valiantly and victoriouſly (by Gods
admirable aſſiſtance) performed by ours, there fell out a moſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable
and ſtrange paſſage, moſt pertinent to this our preſent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
and worthy our moſt ſad and ſerious commemoration, namely,
that among the many ſlaine and dead bodies on the Kings ſide,<note place="margin">7. Gods moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable hand upon Serjeant-major generall <hi>Smith,</hi> ſlaine in the fight at <hi>Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam</hi> bridge, at the ſiege of <hi>Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</hi>
                  </note>
(very many of them being prime Commanders and Officers in
Armes, as was clearely diſcerned by their brave cloathes, pure
fine <hi>Holland</hi>-ſhirts and faire skins, being ſtript naked at the end of
the fight) there was found the body of <hi>Serjeant-major Smith</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
of the Kings Army, a moſt wicked and deſperate Cormo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,
who being a very fat and corpulent fellow, was found with
his belly ript up, and his Greace taken away out of his body;
which very thing (as I had it by moſt credible and that not ſingle
information) this wicked <hi>Smith</hi> had (about a twelve-moneth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
or not ſo much) threatned to act upon the <hi>Round-heads</hi> at
<hi>Okenham,</hi> where ſome of the Kings forces were then quartered, but
driven out by the <hi>Parliaments</hi> forces; where, and at which time of
his enforced departure thence he was heard in a furious threatning
manner to ſay, <hi>Well, farewell Round-heads for this time, but I will
returne againe amongſt you, and then I will rip up your fat panches,
and make medicines of your Greace,</hi> or words to this effect. A moſt
remarkable patterne of the Lords juſtice on him, in ſo punctually
repaying him (<hi>Adonibezech-like</hi>) in his owne coyne. And in the
ſtripping of him (as was credibly reported) they found a Crucifix
about him and other markes of the <hi>Romiſh beaſt,</hi> a fit Champion
(among the reſt) to fight for the maintenance of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi>
Religion.<note place="margin">8. Gods wrath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hand on divers young Gentlemen in a Tavern, abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the City Trainedbands, as they march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on in the ſtreet.</note>
               </p>
               <p>In the yeere alſo, 1642. there hapned another very fearefull
example of <hi>Gods revengefull hand</hi> upon theſe moſt ungodly and
graceleſſe <hi>abuſers</hi> and <hi>tongue-perſecutors</hi> of Gods people, which
was thus; Divers royſtering and ſwaggering yong Gallants, being
drinking in the <hi>Miter-Taverne</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet London,</hi> it ſo fell
out, that in the time of their ſwaggering, ſwearing, and carowſing
in the ſaid Taverne, the <hi>Trained-bands</hi> of the City paſſing by, one
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112665:11"/>
of theſe roaring gallants caſt out ſomething moſt unſeemely out of
the Chamber-window among the ſaid ſouldiers, uſing alſo ſome
very abuſive language againſt them; whereupon, one of them ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
more Gentility and ingenuity of ſpirit than the reſt, reproved
them that did it; whereupon they furiouſly asked him if he were a
<hi>Round-head,</hi> and preſently drew their Swords one upon an other,
and this Gentleman being ſuddenly made at by one of them, puts
by his thruſt, got within him, and ſtab'd him with a Stilletto; the
other two alſo comming on him, he likewiſe wounded them both;
of which three wounded, two of them immediately died, and the
recovery of the third was very queſtionable and dangerous; Which
done, this Gentleman made a way downe the ſtaires with his Sword
in one hand, and the Stillet to in the other, and running downe
<hi>Ram-alley</hi> got to the water and ſo eſcaped away. This I had from
unqueſtionable information, the very morning it was done, I my
ſelfe going into <hi>Fleet-ſtreet</hi> betimes that morning on ſome buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
of mine owne, where and when I heard it exactly and fully
telated to me.</p>
               <p>About the 20 of <hi>Iune</hi> alſo 1643, One M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Haughton</hi> wife to Mr.
<hi>Wil.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">9. A monſtrous and prodigious child borne in Lancaſhire of moſt malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant parents, and the moſt fearfull and remarkable circumſtances in and about it, to the terrour of malignants.</note> 
                  <hi>Haughton</hi> of <hi>Prickmarſh</hi> within the pariſh of <hi>Kirkham</hi> in <hi>Ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi>
in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> was delivered of a child ſtill-borne, which had
no head, yet two eares, two eyes, and a mouth in the breſt of it, and
the hands turning backwards to the elbowes, with a cleft down the
backe; ſo as it was not diſcernable whether it were male or female.
After this child had beene buried two or three daies, the Midwife
teporting its monſtrous and prodigious ſhape &amp; not being credited,
it was thereupon taken out of the grave and reviewed, and was appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently
found to be as is already deſcribed, &amp; as was reported to be;
only a bundle of clouts was taken up with it, which (it ſeems, &amp; was
known) the parents had (in proportion of a head) cauſed to be fitted
unto it. Now that which is very remarkable herein is this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That the
parents of this monſter were (even as their owne parents alſo and
predeceſſours were) notorious profeſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Papiſts,</hi> impudently abuſive
towards <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> curſing and calling them familiarly by the
name of <hi>Round-heads;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that which is yet more memorable
herein, and moſt remarkably worthy our ſerious conſideration,
and moſt clearely demonſtrates that foreſaid prodigious birth to
be <hi>a direct judgement of the Lord</hi> for deſperate <hi>malignancy</hi> againſt the
Lords choice ones, is this, that the <hi>Grandmother</hi> of that <hi>monſter</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:112665:12"/>
was ſhe (whom pious Mr <hi>Prynne</hi> (to her indeleble and perpetuall
infamy) hath already ſet forth in print<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in his famous Hiſtory of
that pair-royall of heroicke ſufferers, Dr. <hi>Baſtwicke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Mr. <hi>Burton,</hi>
and Mr. <hi>Prynne,</hi>) who out of an inveterate malignity againſt, and
in divelliſh derifion of thoſe three foreſaid Worthies, called three
Cats (which ſhe had at that time) by the names of thoſe three preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Chriſtians, and cut off the eares of thoſe her three Cats, both in
deſperate diſdaine (as it ſhould ſeem) of their glorious ſufferings; and
thereby alſo (in ſeeming jollity) to act again that more than <hi>Turkiſh</hi>
Tragedy. And was not here a moſt notable and cleare evidence of
Gods undoubted indignation againſt ſuch intolerably impious and
impudent malignants as theſe, the Lord thus manifeſting that
ſooner or later he will meet with their inſolent and moſt audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
impieties?</p>
               <p>In <hi>November</hi> alſo, 1643. a malignant Souldier (being intended
for ſervice of the <hi>Parliament</hi>) was hanged at <hi>Cambridge</hi> for running
from his Colours, which came thus to paſſe: He with others alſo
in the ſame condemnation being apprehended for the cauſe afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid
and by <hi>Martiall-law</hi> to caſt Dice for their lives;<note place="margin">10. A malignant Souldier hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge for run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from his Colours.</note> this fellow
comming to the Dice, when he threw them out, cryed at the caſt,
<hi>Now, for God and the King, and God receive my ſoule.</hi> Whereupon
it ſo fell out that he caſting the leaſt chance of the Dice, muſt ſuffer
death, and ſo was accordingly executed at the ſame time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Now
that which was very remarkable in Gods hand thus on this fellow
(beſides the voluntary diſcovery of his <hi>Cavalierian-heart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> in thoſe
words, <hi>Now for God and the King,</hi> which is the <hi>Cavallers</hi> common
<hi>ſignall word</hi>) was this, that when he was firſt preſt for a Souldier
he was heard often to ſay, <hi>He would be hang'd before he would fight
for the Parliament.</hi> Even juſt like Sir <hi>Iervaſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wales,</hi> once Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant
of the Tower of <hi>London</hi> in King <hi>Iames</hi> his daies, who was
hanged on <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>er-hill,</hi> for being acceſſary to the poyſoning of Sir
<hi>Thomas Overbury,</hi> then his priſoner in the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ower,</hi> about the Earle
of <hi>Somerſets</hi> buſineſſe. Which Sir <hi>Jervaſe</hi> himſelfe, being on the
Ladder at the Gallowes freely confeſt; That in his life time he had
oft (in his playing at Cards and Dice <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> that he might be hang'd
if it were not ſo and ſo;</hi> and therefore ingenuouſly confeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'d Gods
hand upon him for that ſinne. And ſo ſay I now here, See O thou
unflexible and flinty-hearted malignant, how the Lord moſt juſtly
met with this <hi>malignant spirited Souldier,</hi> paying him moſt palpably
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:112665:12"/>
in his owne Coyne; as this moſt notable and perſonall example
hath moſt clearly declared. This I received out of a Letter ſent by
a religious young Gentleman, a Scholler of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
a very reverend Miniſter of the City of <hi>London,</hi> who gave me
a tranſcript of it, and whoſe teſtimony is, I know, without all
exception.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Cree-church</hi> pariſh alſo, by <hi>Algate</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> one <hi>James At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinſons</hi>
wife, who with her ſaid husband, were both of them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
noted to be moſt <hi>malignant enemies</hi> of the power and purity
of the Goſpell,<note place="margin">11. Gods hand moſt fearefully upon one Mrs. <hi>Atkinſon</hi> in Cree-church pariſh in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
                  </note> and mockers of goodneſſe and good men; which
her ungodly and ill diſpoſition ſhe manifeſted in the Church of
the ſaid pariſh, at a Sermon preached there by reverend and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions
Mr. <hi>Wells</hi> of <hi>New-England,</hi> who in his Sermon, deſired his
auditors that they would not ſleepe; &amp; ſhe being aſleep at that time,
and awakened by one Mrs. <hi>Clarke</hi> her neighbour, a godly Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman
of the ſame pariſh, and that in a very loving and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourly
way, by jogging of her knee as they ſate together in the
Pew; But ſhe preſently upon her awakening fell into ſtrange ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions
of rage and fury, and inſtantly belched out theſe wicked
words, <hi>O you bold drunken flut, doe you kick me?</hi> with divers other
ſuch uncivill ſpeeches. All which the ſaid Mrs. <hi>Clarke</hi> very piouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
and diſcreetly (for the preſent) put up in modeſt and grave ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,
and onely acquainted her husband, a very religious Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
with Mrs. <hi>Atkinſons</hi> ſaid uſage of her in the forenoone, and
therewith expreſſed her unwillingneſſe to fit againe with her in the
Few. Whereupon Mr. <hi>Clarke</hi> unwilling there ſhould be any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
difference between them, at leaſt to continue with any private
heart-burning againſt each other, repaired to the Miniſter of the
ſaid Church, and deſired that he with the Church wardens and
ſome of the ancienteſt of the Pariſh would after the afternoones
Sermon ſend for Mr. <hi>Atkinſon</hi> to ſee whether he would abet or
countenance his wife in this her ill carriage. According to the ſaid
deſire he was ſent for, and came; where, after he had asked the cauſe
of his being ſent for; and Mr. <hi>Clarke</hi> beginning to relate it, <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinſon</hi>
would not ſuffer him to goe on, but he alſo brake forth into
foule words, and told him, <hi>He lied; for Mrs. Clarke, he ſaid, did
kick his wife in the Church.</hi> Whereupon, the Lecturer of the ſaid
Church Mr. <hi>Falkingham,</hi> deſired in love to take him off, intreating
him that each of them might be heard, and ſo the buſineſſe would
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:112665:13"/>
be the better and ſooner reconciled. To whom <hi>Atkinſon</hi> replyed,
<hi>Sir, I have nothing to doe with you; nor you with me.</hi> And to Captaine
<hi>Cower,</hi> who reproved him for ſuch ill behaviour, he ſaid, <hi>You are a
Bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ckhead and a Roundhead;</hi> and thereupon went haſtily and fretfully
out of the <hi>Veſtry,</hi> and fetcht his wife, who alſo came thither in a
great heat, and (very probably) full of bitterneſſe; and ſome cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly
reported, that ſhe had boaſted, being at home, how ſhe had
uſed Mrs. <hi>Clarke.</hi> But moſt certaine it is, that in the <hi>Veſtry,</hi> (being
queſtioned of theſe things) <hi>ſhe wiſhed ſhe might never goe home alive,
if Mrs. Clarke did not kick her, and ſaid, ſhe would have the Law on
her for it.</hi> And both ſhe and her husband did utter many other
bitter words, at, and before this moſt evident token of Gods diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure:
for (as I before touched) it was well knowne that they
both had been a long time much diſaffected to pure religion and
were very ready oft-times, not onely to ſpeake evill of ordinary
Chriſtians, but even of Gods owne Meſſengers; and now, I ſay, at
this time, ſhe eſpecially ſuffering her tongue to wander beyond its
bounds, it pleaſed the Lord that preſently after that fearefull im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precation
upon her ſelfe, afore-mentioned, ſhe was ſtricken ſo ill,
that ſhe began to falter in her ſpeech; inſomuch that thoſe preſent
tooke notice of it, and thereupon ſhe was led forth of the <hi>Veſtry</hi> into
the Church-yard and ſet downe upon a bench there, where ſhe had
meanes uſed for her recovery; but ſhe in a very ſhort time there
died, and was carried home dead: And which is yet more remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably
fearefull, it was credibly affirmed that a little before her
death (in her forementioned weakeneſſe, one of the women about
her had ſaid unto her, that certainely Mrs. <hi>Clarke</hi> would not abuſe
her; but ſhe inſtantly curſed her, ſaying, <hi>A pox on you, you are one of
the holy ſiſters;</hi> and that it was obſerved by ſome at the time of her
death, that her tongue turned blacke in her head. A moſt terrible
and dreadfull example of Gods wrath and indignation, both to her
moſt <hi>malignant husband,</hi> and all <hi>ſuch</hi> irreligious <hi>spirits,</hi> as either in
themſelves, wives, or friends mannage and countenance ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianlike
waies and wicked courſes. All this I have by moſt
unqueſtionable information both from Mr. <hi>Clarke</hi> himſelfe, and
from others who moſt exactly knew the truth of theſe things.</p>
               <p>Upon <hi>Tueſday</hi> alſo <hi>Novemb.</hi> 23. 1642. about 11 of the clocke
at night, the monethly Faſt-day being the very next day after it,
one Captaine <hi>Bard</hi> of Sir <hi>Francis Wortleys</hi> Regiment, with about
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:112665:13"/>
thirty Horſe came from <hi>Ludlow</hi> in the County of <hi>Salop,</hi> of purpoſe
to plunder the houſe of one Mr. <hi>Iohn Green</hi> a reverend, godly, and
learned Divine (and one of the Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi>)
Paſtor of <hi>Pencombe</hi> in the County of <hi>Hereford,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">12. Gods hand moſt remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably upon a Cornet of a Troop of horſe comming to plunder a very godly Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters houſe.</note> being eleven
miles diſtant from the ſaid <hi>Ludlow.</hi> Who being accordingly come
to the ſaid Miniſters houſe, whiles ſome of the Souldiers were
breaking open the doore of his dwelling houſe, one <hi>Ogle</hi> a <hi>Northern
man</hi> and a <hi>Cornet</hi> of the ſaid Troope of Horſe was the firſt that
brake open the ſtable doore; and as ſoone as ever the ſaid <hi>Ogle</hi> was
ſtepping over the threſhold to goe into the ſtable firſt, as the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
ſervants who lay in a chamber adjoyning to the ſtable repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
and teſtified) he fell downe as dead into the ſtable, and in the
morning his Hat and a ſmall Piece were found in the ſtable behind
a ſtone-horſe (which ſtood in a ſtall next the ſtable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> doore, which
was made up ſo firme with plankes and barres both behind and on
each ſide of him, that he could not poſſibly ſtrike him) and ſo
ſome of the other Souldiers brought him into the ſaid Miniſters
houſe as a dead man, the Captaine ſaying, that he fainted for want
of meat, and ſo deſired that ſome comfortable refreſhing might
be given him. Then they placed him in a Chaire, and ſo having
plundered what they thought fit from the godly Miniſter, they
left the Cornet there and returned to <hi>Ludlow.</hi> About ſome 2 houres
after he began to revive, and a little to come to his ſpeech, and the
firſt words he uttered (after an imperfect manner, were, <hi>Holy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of God helpe me;</hi> and by his often croſſing of himſelfe, and by
the teſtimony of others there that knew him, he was diſcovered to
be a profeſt <hi>Papiſt.</hi> Thus he continued a ſenceleſſe man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his head,
hands, and joynts of his body, ſeeming quite looſe, he ſpake very
little and ſeldome and imperfectly, did eate whatever was given
him, and would plucke raw meat from the ſpit newly laid to the
fire and offer to eate it; and as he ſate in his chaire, if he offered to
leane forward, he would fall into the fire; if he leaned backward,
he would fall downe backward; and one night he was found under
his bed wrapt up in one of the ſheets onely in his ſhirt. The wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
that attended and watched with him, upon a diligent ſearch
of his body, could not diſcerne or perceive any bruiſe or ſo much as
diſcolouring of his skinne in any part of his body; whereby they
all could not but clearely conceive and believe it to be the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate
hand of God upon him; and at that time ſome of his owne
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:112665:14"/>
Companions were heard to ſay, (as was credibly informed) <hi>Let us
be gone hence, for God fights againſt us.</hi> This ſaid <hi>Cornet</hi> being ſent
for to <hi>Ludlow</hi> upon the Saturday following the Souldiers at his
firſt comming ſeeing him in that ſenceleſſe condition, ſaid, <hi>Sure he
was drunke;</hi> but he ſtill continued after the very ſame manner as was
forementioned, without ſence or underſtanding, and a little time
after (as the Captaine himſelfe reported) died in that ſenceleſneſſe.
All this being teſtified for moſt true, both by the ſaid reverend Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter
Mr. <hi>Greene</hi> himſelfe, by his ſervants, and divers others who
were eye-witneſſes of all theſe premiſes.</p>
               <p>About the midſt of <hi>Ianuary</hi> alſo,<note place="margin">13. Gods imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable hand upon one <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence Hyde,</hi> a deſperate ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant againſt the Parliament</note> 1643. there fell out a moſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable
and fearefull example of Gods immediate puniſhing hand
(neere unto the City of <hi>Salisbury</hi>) upon a moſt peſtilent and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate
<hi>malignant</hi> and perſecuter of Gods people in thoſe parts;
namely, one <hi>Laurence Hyde</hi> a Commiſſioner of enquiry after all
ſuch as had either given or lent any thing for the <hi>Parliaments</hi>
ſervice; who the very ſame day that <hi>Heath, Bankes, Foſter,</hi> and
<hi>Glanvill,</hi> thoſe wicked <hi>Oxonian</hi> Earthwormes, Judges, and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers
of illegalities, came into the City of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> to keepe the
Aſſizes there) having threatned moſt vigorouſly to proſecute all
the <hi>Roundheads</hi> in thoſe parts at the ſaid Aſſizes; and thus riding
with his Commiſſion (as <hi>Saul</hi> to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> though not with
ſuch a bleſſed blow to beat him off from his horſe to holy repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance)
as he was haſtily riding on, within a mile of the ſaid City
he ſuddenly fell from his Horſe and ſo brake his necke or his
ſhoulder-bone in the fall, that thereby he inſtantly died before
he could be brought alive into the Towne. Being thus by Gods
moſt evident and heavy hand upon him, cut ſhort and deprived
of power to doe that miſchiefe to Gods honeſt and innocent
hidden-ones, which (as 'twas well knowne) he had frequently
before menaced againſt them. The truth of this I have confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
unto me, not onely by the printed relation, (but as my cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome
is in all ſuch like occaſions) upon diligent enquiry from
ſuch honeſt and credible teſtimony,<note place="margin">14. Gods hand upon 3 malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Citizens, being all three neighbours to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether on Lud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate-hill in <hi>London.</hi>
                  </note> as I know to be without all
exception.</p>
               <p>There were alſo three neighbours dwelling on <hi>Ludgate-hill</hi> in
<hi>London,</hi> two of them <hi>Hoſiers,</hi> dwelling directly one over againſt
the other, the third a <hi>Wollen-Draper,</hi> who lived next doore to one
of the <hi>Hoſiers,</hi> all three of them of one minde in <hi>malignancy,</hi> and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:112665:14"/>
inveterate enemies to the <hi>Parliaments</hi> proceedings. One of theſe
<hi>Hoſiers</hi> in the moneth of January 1642. did intimate unto the
other <hi>Hoſier</hi> his deſire and purpoſe to goe to <hi>Oxford,</hi> which the
other underſtanding, conſented and promiſed to goe along with
him, and accordingly away they went, and what their worke
and buſineſſe was there, though not certainly knowne, yet may be
eaſily judged, no goodneſſe, to be ſure of it; but about a weeke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
one of them having ſpent (as 'twas beleeved) all his ſpare pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall
money, or done his wicked worke, returned backe againe
to his houſe in <hi>London;</hi> the other ſtayed there longer behinde, and
came not backe with him. Within a few dayes after the returne
home of the ſaid <hi>Hoſier,</hi> he with his ſaid neighbour the malignant
<hi>Woollen-Draper,</hi> went (as it was knowne to be their cuſtome) to
the Taverne, called <hi>The Devill and Saint Dunſtones</hi> neere <hi>Temple-Barre,</hi>
together with ſome others, <hi>ejuſdem farinae,</hi> of the ſame tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
or untempered mouldy-<hi>Malignancy,</hi> their buſineſſe there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to be mad-merry, and to drinke healths to Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> that
Prince of Plunderers, the Atheiſticall <hi>Marqueſſe of Newcaſtle,</hi>
and ſuch others of that rotten-rout: Now it ſo fell out that one
of their Companions proved more civill then the reſt, and ſhewed
his diſlike of theſe their doings; whereupon the <hi>Hoſier</hi> began to
quarrell with that man, and from their wrangling diſcourſe they
both fell to fighting, and as the <hi>Hoſier</hi> was ſtrugling with the ſaid
party, there comes a third man and violently pulled the <hi>Hoſier</hi> off,
who inſtantly fell backward, and with the fall brake his legge,
whereof he lay under cure a long time after. The <hi>Woollen-Draper,</hi>
his foreſaid Aſſociate, being a prodigall Spend-thrift, and runne
much in debt to his Creditors, they (on the very ſame day of this
their drinking in the ſaid Taverne, and at the very ſame inſtant
time of his drinking healths there) came with Serjeants and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers,
ſeized on all his clothes and goods, whereof hee hearing,
and knowing himſelfe thereby undone in his eſtate, inſtantly fled
away, and was no more ſeene. The third partie of the foreſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly
ſociety, to wit, the other <hi>Hoſier,</hi> (late ſervant to one <hi>Pate,</hi>
a moſt deſperate Malignant alſo againſt God and the Parliament,
and a notorious ſcoffer at godlineſſe and good men) who, I told
you before, continued at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and came not home with his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<hi>Hoſier,</hi> abiding ſtill, I ſay, behinde at <hi>Oxford,</hi> kept continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
company with the <hi>Kings Cormorants</hi> there, drinking and ſwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:112665:15"/>
day and night in their deboiſt company, and that in ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive
and immoderate meaſure, that he was not onely drunke, but
fell mad among them; in ſo much that getting his horſe out of the
Stable, he moſt deſperately rode up and downe the ſtreets there,
till at laſt being eſpied by ſome Citizens of <hi>London</hi> that knew him,
who perceived quickly in what condition he was, and being for
<hi>London</hi> themſelves at that time, they brought him home with them,
with no little adoe by the way; who being thus brought home,
continued ſo diſtracted and beſotted in his ſenſes, that he neither
regarded what any ſaid or did to him, and wholly neglected his
calling, as being unfit to doe ought therein, and ſhortly after hee
fell ſicke for a ſeaſon, and ſtill continued ſo diſtracted, that at laſt
it was held fit to have him away to <hi>Bedlem;</hi> yet for ſome credit
ſake, his friends ſo prevailed, that he was not put into the common
condition of the Madmen there, but was kept private in the houſe
of one that endeavours the cure of ſuch perſons, and there he was
continued, but could not be cured of this his miſerable and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted
eſtate. And was not here a moſt evident and remarkable
hand of God upon them all three, to the terrour (one would
thinke) of all ſuch deſperate and incorrigible <hi>Malignants.</hi> All
which relation I have received from ſuch honeſt and credible teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
of the truth thereof, even of ſuch as knew the three par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
very well, as is without all juſt exception therein.</p>
               <p>And thus now, I have (as I ſuppoſe) ſufficienly made good my
word, and performed my promiſe in the two former parts of this
my <hi>Looking-glaſſe,</hi> namely, in moſt clearly repreſenting and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
forth to the eyes and underſtanding of every one, of any one
that is <hi>compos mentis,</hi> and is not ſtarke mad with malice and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief,
both <hi>Gods hand</hi> moſt eminently <hi>againſt our Anti-Parliament a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi>
or <hi>Malignants, and alſo Gods evident heavy hand upon thoſe
our Malignants perſons, even immediately in the very acting of their
malignancy.</hi> Enough, one would thinke, to fright and terrifie
them from ſuch impious and audacious flouting, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onting, and
maligning of Gods honeſt and harmleſſe ſervants, were not their
Conſciences cauterized with the hot iron of graceleſſe impenetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
obſtinacy, and their hearts more hardned (againſt pure and
innocent <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Holineſſe</hi>) than the impenetrable Tortice
ſhell, and they thereby even given over by God to a reprobate ſenſe,
to their irrecoverable ruine and perdition.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:112665:15"/>
But now, to goe on to my <hi>Third</hi> promiſed <hi>part</hi> or <hi>repreſentation</hi>
in this our <hi>Looking-glaſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3. A Caveat for Cowards and Neutrall-De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerters of the Parliaments Cauſe.</note> namely, the <hi>Caveat for Cowards and faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted
Neutrall-Deſerters of the Parliaments cauſe;</hi> and therein, I
ſay moſt clearly, <hi>Gods cauſe.</hi> As alſo hereby to ſpeake to all <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetled
and unreſolved weake Chriſtians</hi> (whom in this caſe we muſt
pitty, pardon, and pray for, as being our ſelves ſubject to like
failings and errours, ſhould not grace prevent and ſupport us) to
ſhew them the great danger and hard hazards they put themſelves
on, both in ſoule and body too, in ſo unworthily fearing or refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
to owne Gods Cauſe,<note place="margin">A briefe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Pream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of this Caveat.</note> though not out of <hi>treachery,</hi> yet if it be
but of baſe <hi>timidity</hi> or feare; God herein ſhewing his wrath and
indignation, and cauſing his jealouſie to breake out againſt theſe
alſo, letting them ſee how dangerous it is to jeſt or dally with ſuch
ſharp edg'd tooles as theſe to the undoing of their ſoules and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
too, I ſay, if in his owne free grace and meere mercy he did
not in the midſt of juſtice remember to intermix mercy, and to
looke backe, as it were, on their ſinking ſoules, as he did on <hi>Peter</hi>
in ſuch a caſe (if at leaſt they belong to <hi>Chriſt</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> did) tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
them thereby to know the price of denying their <hi>Maſter</hi>
or his <hi>Cauſe</hi> before men, if not, I ſay, prevented by true and timely
repentance. All which I ſhall make moſt evident and cleare by
theſe foure or five Examples, all of them fallen out lately in theſe
our probationall times, which (by Gods providence) have come
to my hands and knowledge, and which for the <hi>glory of God</hi> and
<hi>honour</hi> of our moſt precious <hi>Parliaments Cauſe,</hi> I could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale,
but ſet forth moſt faithfully, as I have received them from
moſt indubitable and unqueſtionable Teſtimonies of the truth of
them all; even, I ſay, by thoſe who were both Eye and Ear-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes
of the truth of them.</p>
               <p>And here now in the firſt place, I might inſtance in a learned and
reverend Miniſter of <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. A Doctor in Divinity of Lincolnſhire fell mad upon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the taking of the Oxonian Proteſtation againſt the Parliament.</note> a <hi>Doctor in Divinity,</hi> who being
taken by the Kings Cormorants, and carried priſoner to <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke,</hi>
and there enforced to take the <hi>Oxonian</hi> Proteſtation or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> which (it ſeemes) out of ſervile
feare and unworthy puſillanimity, he did, immediately after it, out
or remorſe of Conſcience, fell mad and fearfully diſtracted in his
ſenſes, and ſo continued for almoſt the ſpace of halfe a yeere, this
being done by him about the midſt of the laſt Summer 1643. but
being ſince at liberty among his <hi>Parliamentary</hi> friends, is in good
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:112665:16"/>
meaſure recovered, and a hearty Penitent for it. But it being deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
his name ſhould bee concealed, I ceaſe to ſay any more there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
ſave onely this, That I have this briefe relation from ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable
and credible teſtimony as moſt ſtrongly confirmes the
truth thereof unto me. And might we not, here now, thinke this
one ſingle example ſufficient, to deter our cowardly Newters from
ſo vicious and pernicious prejudicating and deſerting the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi>
pious proceedings? Yes certainly, had they but any ſmall
ſparkes of ingenuity left alive in them: but ſince I know that they,
yea, and Gods owne people too, muſt have line upon line (as the
Prophet ſayes) and example upon example, and all too too little,
till Gods Spirit of Grace awakens their dead and drouſie Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences.
I ſhall now give them another Example which comes more
cloſe unto them, and moſt worthy their deep and ſerious obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
and conſideration, which briefly is this:</p>
               <p>Upon the ſecond day of May 1643. one <hi>Thomas Bretton</hi> a young
man,<note place="margin">2. One <hi>Thomas Bretton,</hi> a moſt bitter and active Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably converted on his death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed.</note> and moſt bitter and active <hi>Malignant</hi> againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi>
late ſervant to Alderman <hi>Cullum</hi> in <hi>Gracious ſtreet</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
very ſick (which indeed ſhortly after proved a ſickneſſe unto
death) deſired moſt earneſtly to ſpeake with a reverend and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Miniſter of the City, whom he had formerly heard preach,
and could not be quiet till he was ſent for. The Miniſter being ſent
unto, and intreated to come unto him accordingly, very willingly
came; of whom (ſo ſoone as the ſicke party ſaw him) he moſt
heartily deſired his pardon and forgiveneſſe. The Miniſter anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
That he knew not any thing wherein the ſick party had injured
or offended him. But <hi>Bretton</hi> replied, <hi>That he had done him wrong in
jeering and ſcoffing at him, though he knew not of it,</hi> and told him
the particulars thereof. Whereupon this pious Miniſter told him,
He freely forgave him. Then he deſired the Miniſter to pray with
him, which he alſo did for the ſpace of about halfe an houre. Imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately
after Prayer the ſicke party ſaid, He was now moſt happy,
ſince God and Man had forgiven him; and told the Miniſter,
hee was certaine God pardoned him all his finnes. The Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
anſwered, It was well, if his aſſurance were on good grounds.
He replied, That he was ſure of it, for Chriſt had taken away all
his ſinnes, which God had in his ſickneſſe ſet before his eyes; yea,
and ſome ſuch finnes as he did not know or beleeve formerly to
have beene ſinnes; but now Chriſt had borne them all on his owne
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:112665:16"/>
ſhoulders, and eaſed him of all that heavy burthen, with many
other moſt heavenly and divine expreſſions. And being neere his
death, even the night before he died, he ſaid, Hee aſſuredly ſaw
Chriſt in a viſion appearing unto him, and telling him that his
ſinnes were pardoned, and that he had a <hi>Cauſe</hi> on earth, and that
the <hi>Parliament of England</hi> defended it, and that in the yeere of our
Lord Chriſt 1644. the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhould obtaine a great victory
over the Kings Forces; and that then there ſhould bee none of
thoſe wicked Miniſters (that had miſ-led Gods people) left among
them, and that from that time the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhould proſper; but
in the meane ſeaſon, that <hi>the rod of the wicked ſhould reſt on the
backs of his righteous ones.</hi> And after this hee lay glorying
and rejoycing in the forgiveneſſe of his ſinnes, and even triumph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
over death till the time of his departure, which was the next
day. This relation was teſtified both by the ſaid learned, reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend,
and religious <hi>Divine,</hi> who was often with him in his ſaid
ſickneſſe, and heard moſt of his expreſſions; and alſo by another
religious <hi>Gentleman</hi> who was alſo then preſent, and heard what is
here delivered, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Alſo one <hi>Thomas Clarke,</hi> a ranke malignant young man, and
ſervant to one Maſter <hi>Travill</hi> a merchant of <hi>London,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3. One <hi>Thomas Clarke</hi> alſo, a merchants man in <hi>London,</hi> a notable malignant, his penitent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion on his death-bed in honour of the Parliament.</note> being
in the yeere 1643) ſtricken with ſickneſſe, of which he died;
about three dayes before his death, one <hi>William Coote</hi> (a neighbour
of his) comming to viſit him in this his ſickneſſe, and having ſate a
while with him, as he was going away the ſick party deſired him to
ſtay a little, and told him, that hee would now ſay more to him
then he had done to any, which was this, I am now (ſayes hee)
ſtrongly perſwaded in my heart, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> maintains a
right cauſe, and at laſt ſhall have victory over the <hi>Kings Forces,</hi> for
they, he ſaid, fought for <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> and he confeſt withall, that
he had lived a very ſinfull life, and was moſt of all grieved that he
had ſpoken ſo much againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> for which he wiſhed
he could now weep teares of blood, together with very many pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theticall
ſpeeches to this purpoſe, and ſhortly after it departed this
life. This I have alſo from very honeſt and religious hands and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony,
who have faithfully informed me of the truth thereof, as
having been both eye and ear-witneſſes of the ſame.</p>
               <p>In September alſo 1643. one Maſter <hi>Whitleigh</hi> in <hi>Golding, lane</hi> in
<hi>London,</hi> with his wife Miſtreſſe <hi>Whitleigh,</hi> both of them very
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:112665:17"/>
religious Chriſtians,<note place="margin">4. A remarkable example of one Maſter <hi>Whitleigh</hi> and his wife, who deſerted the Cauſe of the Parliament.</note> and truly fearing the Lord, came with their
foure children (not long before) to <hi>London</hi> from <hi>Tewksbury</hi> in
<hi>Glouceſterſhire,</hi> principally deſiring to remove thence becauſe of the
wicked converſation of the Cavaliers, billeted where he lived.
And hee having formerly ſerved in the <hi>Parliaments</hi> Army againſt
the <hi>Kings Forces,</hi> but being now at <hi>London,</hi> and for about three
moneths ſpace void of imployment, reſolved to give over ſervice
in the wars, as finding a timorous fearfulneſſe in himſelfe to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture
any more into the <hi>Parliaments</hi> Army, thereupon at laſt
he had ſome thoughts to goe into <hi>New-England,</hi> and adviſing
with his wife, who alſo was moſt unw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing hee ſhould any more
put himſelfe into the Service of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> but by all meanes
began to ſtrengthen his reſolution to goe away for <hi>New-England.</hi>
Whereupon he peremptorily now reſolving to depart thither with
his wife and children, preſently laid out thirty pounds for their
paſſage by Sea, and as much more for proviſion of neceſſaries to
the voyage. But being ready to depart, the Lord ſuddenly ſtruck
him very ſicke, and in his ſickneſſe he was very much troubled in
his minde, lamenting and crying out very much againſt the ſinne of
Cowardiſe and Fearfulneſſe (which hee conceived to bee the
ground of his intended removall to <hi>New-England</hi>) and therefore
much diſtruſting his ſoules eſtate, cryed out often, That he had
ſinned againſt God in cowardly deſerting his <hi>holy Cauſe;</hi> yet ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly
praying the Lord to forgive him this ſinne, promiſing and
proteſting that if the Lord vouchſafed to reſtore him to health
and ſtrength againe, he would reſolutely goe on to ſpend every
drop of the blood in his veines for the <hi>Parliaments Cauſe;</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward
blaming his wife for giving her conſent and incouraging
him therein, he ſhortly after died, yet before his departure he te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified
abundance of comfort and aſſurance of Gods favour and
the pardon of his ſin. Immediately alſo after his death, it ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
the Lord that his wife fell ſo diſtracted, that three or foure
women could ſcarcely hold her downe in her bed, and ſhe taking
no ſuſtenance but what was forced into her mouth for many dayes,
ſhe ſtill in all this time of moſt ſad perplexity crying out, That
ſhe had ſinned againſt God in counſelling and incouraging her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed
husband to forſake <hi>Gods Cauſe,</hi> and thereby (ſhe feare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>) ſhe
had beene the cauſe of his death. And thus ſhe lay divers dayes in
much miſery, crying out of this her ſinne, and craving pardon of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:112665:17"/>
God for it. And about the end of September aforeſaid, my godly
friend, from whom I had this relation, comming occaſionally to her
houſe to ſee her, found that her raging fits had left her, but her
ſpirits much ſpent, and ſhe lying ſpeechleſſe, ſo that he knew not
how to adminiſter a word of comfort to her in that caſe; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
being about to depart thence, ſhee looked ſtedfaſtly on him,
reached out her hand to him, which he tooke in his, being as
cold as clay, and therewith ſpake many comfortable words unto
her, and ere he departed ſhe manifeſted very much conſolation
in her ſoule, both by words (though faintly) and geſtures alſo,
and in a moſt happy and comfortable condition departed this life
alſo, the very next morning after his departure from her. This re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,
I ſay, I had from a very religious Citizen of <hi>London,</hi> and
faithfull ſervant of the Lord, who himſelfe was with Miſtreſſe
<hi>Whitleigh</hi> thus departing, and whoſe own Siſter lived cloſe by theſe
parties, was well acquainted with them both in their lives and
death, and whoſe teſtimony I know to be without exception.</p>
               <p>There was alſo about the time of the firſt victories of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
and renowned Towne of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">5. One Maſter <hi>Standidge</hi> a Lancaſhire Gentleman, deſerting the Parliament, ſuddenly ſlaine in the act of his defection.</note> in the
yeere 1642. one M. <hi>Standidge</hi> a Gentleman of <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> who
had formerly beene a man much ingaged in his affections for the
<hi>Parliaments Cauſe,</hi> and had oftentimes expreſſed ſo much both
by his ſtiffe contendings with ſome that were very neere and deare
unto him, as alſo by his practice and aſſiſtance given to the ſaid
Cauſe. But afterward, by the ſlye inſinuations and perſwaſions
of ſome ſeeming friends neere about him; but eſpecially being at
laſt overſwaied and prevailed with (as was ſtrongly ſuppoſed) by
the Lord <hi>Strange</hi> (then a great, but, bleſſed be God, a moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucceſſefull
ſtickler for the Kings party) he being very intimate
with the ſaid Lord <hi>Strange.</hi> This ſaid Gentleman did at laſt ſo
much croſſe his owne former practice and good eſteeme he had and
held of the Worke and Cauſe of God in the <hi>Parliaments</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings,
that he moſt unworthily quite deſerted it, yea ſo farre
as to take up Armes againſt it; and as he was in perſon, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
and going againſt that honeſt, famous, and victorious Town
of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> in the Lord <hi>Stranges</hi> Army; the Lord God of
Heaven, in apparent diſpleaſure met with him in this moſt diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
Apoſtacie, and going againſt God and his Cauſe: For as he
was going to take Horſe upon ſome deſigne, neere to the ſaid Town
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:112665:18"/>
of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> a bullet ſuddenly hit him, and kil'd him pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently,
not directly from the Towne, but the bullet glancing
upon a wall, reached him with a gliding blow, and ſo cut him
ſhort of his purpoſe, and gave him the ſad reward of his unhappy
backſliding. This I have from ſuch unqueſtionable and religious
teſtimony of a godly friend and neighbour of mine, as I know to
be without all juſt exception.</p>
               <p>And is not here now (one would thinke) teſtimony enough for
thee, O incredulous Malignant, yea, even from the mouthes of two
Converts formerly of thine owne ranke and rotten condition, but
now, and that upon their death-beds (<hi>and the words of dying
men we know, doe, or ought to take deepe impreſſion</hi>) making ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
confeſſion of their and your folly and madneſſe in ſo injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
oppoſing the pious and juſt proceedings of the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
But now take one more to cleare theſe truths yet more
abundantly,<note place="margin">6. A moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Joſeph Latch</hi> a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, his great miſery for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting the Parliament, and his merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full recovery.</note> yea, one of no leſſe moment and materiality then
any of the former, and moſt worthy ſerious notice and obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
namely, of one Maſter <hi>Ioſeph Latch,</hi> a Merchant in <hi>Baſhings<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall-ſtreet</hi>
in <hi>London,</hi> who having (by Gods bleſſing upon his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours
in his calling) gotten a good eſtate, and being a pious
young Gentleman, and well affected to the publike good of the
Kingdome in the beginning of this Parliamentary warre, and ſet
forth two Horſes for the ſaid ſervice at his owne proper charge;
but having ſome conſiderable goods at <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> which he deſired
to convey to <hi>Mancheſter</hi> by land, in which land-paſſage a prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
from the King was neceſſary for their ſafe convoy thorow
<hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> where lay a Garriſon of the Kings Cormorants: up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
this occaſion hee forced himſelfe to goe to <hi>Oxford</hi> to procure
ſuch a protection. Thus then he tooke his journey thither, where
he was no ſooner arrived, but it pleaſed the Lord it ſhould ſo fall
out, that he was preſently eſpied by one that had beene a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant
neighbour of his in <hi>London,</hi> a Lawyer, by whoſe meanes
he was preſently apprehended as a Spie, on which ſuſpicion hee
was inſtantly clapt up priſoner in the Caſtle, and immediatly after
was fetcht before the <hi>Councell-Table,</hi> and in danger of his life.
But having there very good friends of the Kings party, namely, Sir
<hi>George Binion,</hi> Sir <hi>Nicholas Criſpe,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bradborne</hi> his kinſman,
and others, he was by the Kings owne Warrant ſet at liberty and
entertained at Sir <hi>George Binious</hi> lodgings; and yet againe for all
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:112665:18"/>
this, <hi>Smith</hi> that helliſh <hi>Cerberus,</hi> the Provoſt-marſhall fetcht him
out of <hi>Bynions</hi> lodgings at eleven of the clocke at night, and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
him to priſon againe. Whereupon <hi>Bynion</hi> went againe to the
King, together with Mr. <hi>Bradborne,</hi> told His Majeſty of it, who
ſeemed much diſcontented thereat, and preſently ſent a Squire of
His body with a Commiſſion to lay <hi>Smith</hi> by the heeles for his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption,
and to enlarge Mr. <hi>Latch;</hi> yea, and that without taking
the <hi>Oxford Proteſtation,</hi> leſt thereby his eſtate in <hi>London</hi> ſhould
have been ſeized on by the <hi>Parliament,</hi> as the eſtate of a <hi>Sworne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malignant,</hi>
yet with a private ſerious promiſe and engagement to
<hi>Bynion,</hi> that he would never hereafter put forth himſelfe in any
publique ſervice for the <hi>Parliament.</hi> So he at laſt returned ſafely
home, and in order to his promſe was now growen very ſhy of
ſerving with his Company according to the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia;</hi>
and ſhortly after, through the ill-advice of a very malignant
companion of his, made over his eſtate into <hi>Holland,</hi> put off his
houſe in <hi>Baſhing ſhall</hi>-ſtreet, and then withdrew his perſon alſo into
<hi>Holland,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Thus our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh <hi>Jonas</hi> would have fled from <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neve</hi> to <hi>Tarſhiſh,</hi> but God raiſed a ſtorme in his conſcience, which drove him backe to our <hi>London Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neve</hi> there to cry repentance.</note> intending there to have lived till theſe times might change;
and thus he quite deſerted the <hi>Parliament.</hi> But he had not beene
there above three weekes or a moneth, but that it pleaſed God he
fell ſicke there, and had a great and reſtleſſe deſire to come backe
againe into <hi>England;</hi> and accordingly, having a fit opportunity,
imbarked himſelfe, and was brought backe ſicke to <hi>London,</hi> that
thus by the providence of God ſo ordering it, he might manifeſt
his repentance here where he had finned, and be an example to
others both of the horrour which ariſes out of a guilty conſcience
ſenſible of apoſtacy from a good Cauſe, and alſo from our <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary
Proteſtation</hi> and <hi>Covenant</hi> to maintaine the ſame. Thus
then, I ſay, being come off the water, on Munday <hi>Sept.</hi> 25. 1643.
he went to a friends houſe of his, one Mr. <hi>Lacey</hi> in <hi>Canon-ſtreet,</hi>
where he went ſicke to bed, and in two daies his ſickneſſe and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
working together, he much deſired to ſpeake with ſome
godly Miniſter. Whereupon one was ſent for, who accordingly
came to him on the Wedneſday night; but knowing nothing of his
defection from the Parliament, and hearing a good report of his
former honeſt converſation, he onely queſtioned him about his
faith in Chriſt; whereunto receiving an appoſite anſwer, he held
out unto him ſome promiſes of the Goſpell, wherein his ſoule
might cleave unto the Lord, and having commended him unto the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:112665:19"/>
grace of God, departed for that time; but Mr. <hi>Latch</hi> found ſuch
ſweetneſſe in thoſe promiſes, that he ſtill would be asking when
that Miniſter would come againe. That <hi>Thurſday</hi> and <hi>Friday</hi> paſt,
and the Miniſter not ſent for; but on the <hi>Saturday</hi> following he
called very earneſtly for the ſaid Miniſter, and would not be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
without him: ſo he being ſent for, came to him that <hi>Saturday</hi>
at night, and found him very anxious about getting Chriſt, he oft
ſaying, if I have not Chriſt, I muſt periſh eternally. But immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately
after, as a man ſwallowed up of deſpaire and drenched in the
wrath of God, he cried out, I am in Hell, I am in Hell. Then an
honeſt young Gentleman his loving friend, who had been his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-apprentiſe,
and unto whom he had uſed to unboſome him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
ſtept to the Miniſter and told him what was the cauſe of all
this horrour of conſcience in him, and ſo related to him the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
of all fore-mentioned. Then the ſaid Miniſter went againe
to M. <hi>Latch,</hi> and asked him if he had taken the Kings <hi>Proteſtation at
Oxford,</hi> who anſwered, no; yet ſtill rejected (in a deſperate manner)
all the comfortable words that were alledged for his faith to reſt
upon; ſtill crying out, I am in hell, I ſinke lower and lower; O
was there ever ſuch an hypocrite as I am, and therefore I muſt be
damned, and I alone muſt have my portion with <hi>Iudas,</hi> and be an
example to all the world and lie in hell to all eternity, in ſo deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the <hi>Parliament:</hi> and goe, ſaies he, to his brother that ſtood by
him, and tell ſuch an one, and ſuch an one, two perſons to whom
he had neere relation, that if they hold on their way, they muſt
burne in hell as I doe; and neither his godly friend, nor the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
could perſwade him that he was out of Hell; yet the Miniſter
ſtill moſt piouſly wreſtling againſt his deſpaire, told him that Hell
was not above ground (in the Land of the living) and therefore
he was not yet in Hell, but that he ſhould goe to Hell ſhortly if he
would not believe in Chriſt Jeſus; and then told him he would
pray for him: But he replied, you ſhall ſave the Flocke of Chriſt,
but you cannot ſave me, I am paſt prayer. And with the like lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
ſpeeches, as of a man in the very torments of the damned;
he did oft interrupt the Miniſter in his prayer, and ſo continued
in this deſpairing fit till after prayer. Then the Miniſter charged
him to hearken to him, ſaying, You never (you aſſure me) tooke
the <hi>Proteſtation</hi> at <hi>Oxford</hi> againſt the Parliament, but <hi>Peter</hi> denied
Chriſt with an <hi>Oath,</hi> yea and with a <hi>Curſe</hi> too; yet he went out
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:112665:19"/>
and wept bitterly, and was reſtored to grace and favour againe.
Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Come unto me all ye that are weary and heavy laden, and
I will give you reſt:</hi> you are weary and heavy laden, come to Chriſt,
believe in him, and he will eaſe you, and will blot out your iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
for his owne names ſake. At which words, he ſuddenly raiſed
up himſelfe in his bed, and with exceeding earneſtneſſe of ſpirit
put forth ſtrong cries unto God, ſaying, <hi>Lord helpe mine unbeliefe,
Lord helpe mine unbeliefe, Lord helpe mine unbeliefe,</hi> three times
together; and immediately thereupon burſt forth into exceeding
great comfort, ſaying, O wonderfull mercy, Chriſt is come to
fetch me out of Hell, and I ſhall not periſh; my cries have entered
into the eares of the Lord of Sabbath, who hath now given ſweet
reſt to my ſoule. And thus with many heavenly expreſſions of
Chriſts wonderfull mercy toward him, he continued at leaſt two
houres full of ſweet raptures and raviſhments of ſoule; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought
the Miniſter and his friends about him to make knowne
theſe things, and how gracious and mercifull Chriſt had been
unto him: and this alſo he deſired them to take ſpeciall notice of;
namely, that he proteſted that what he had ſaid (as before) was not
out of any lightneſſe or diſtemper of his braine, but in ſenſible ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions
of his ſoule, and what Chriſt had dictated to him, in
whoſe armes he ſaid he now was moſt ſweetly imbraced, and that
he had now found (as he had often heard) that as the way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
was by the gates of Hell; ſo he had found it true, and had not
onely gone by the gates of Hell, but even through Hell it ſelfe, but
now Chriſts glorious mercy had fetcht him forth; and therefore
he prayed them againe to tell and publiſh abroad what great things
Chriſt had done for him, and then all that were preſent went
againe to prayer, and he prayed with them; and when his breath
failed, he would lift up his hands; but before prayer was quite en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
he moſt ſweetly expired, as he ſaid, in the Armes of his ſweet
Saviour Chriſt Jeſus, leaving the Miniſter and his Chriſtian friends
(who had been ſorrowfull witneſſes of the former dreadfull people<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xities
and horrour of his conſcience) now moſt abundantly cheered
and full of comfort and conſolation in the Lord, for this admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
gracious change and concluſion.</p>
               <p>And now, I hope, I have fully performed what I promiſed at
the beginning, and have copiouſly confirmed the truchs I intended
to deliver and repreſent in this my <hi>Looking-glaſſe.</hi> And now I ſhall
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:112665:20"/>
onely deſire to ſumme up all in a very ſuccinct <hi>hortatory obſervation</hi>
of all hitherto delivered in this our <hi>Malignants mirrour</hi> or <hi>Looking-glaſſe.</hi>
And firſt I deſire to ſpeake a word or two to our cowardly
<hi>Neuters,</hi> and faint hearted <hi>deſerters</hi> of Gods <hi>Cauſe</hi> in this our <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament;</hi>
wherein I feare too many even of Gods children (and
otherwiſe good Chriſtians, I hope) are too guilty. That ſince the
<hi>Parliaments cauſe</hi> is unqueſtionably <hi>Gods cauſe,</hi> and that our <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants</hi>
have clearely ſeene that God is ſo jealous of this his <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
Cauſe,</hi> that he will not ſpare even his owne Servants, if
they either reject or neglect his <hi>Cauſe</hi> before men, and that he
will certainly ſooner or later wound their <hi>conſciences</hi> with terrour,
if they thinke to wound his <hi>cauſe,</hi> with either <hi>treachery</hi> or <hi>timidity</hi>
and baſe <hi>cowardiſe;</hi> let them not, I ſay, thinke to ſleepe in a whole
skin, to ſhrinke their necks out of the coller and doe well enough
for all that: for certainely God can and will find them out at laſt,
as they alſo may have ſeene in theſe former examples of two or
three, even of Gods deare children, who like <hi>Ionas</hi> would needs be
flying from <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>cauſe,</hi> one into <hi>New-England,</hi> and another
into <hi>Holland,</hi> but how the Lord found them out, cauſed them to
ſee their faithleſſe folly, and ere he was reconciled to them ſmar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
them both ſoundly for it; and though he come ſlowly and (as
the obſervation is) with <hi>Leaden-heeles,</hi> yet will come ſorely, and
with <hi>Iron-hands,</hi> as hath been here before moſt evidently ſeen. And
let them often ruminate and remember (and that with trembling)
what the Spirit of God ſaies in the booke of the <hi>Revelations,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Revel. 21. 7. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>He
that overcommeth (that is,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 3. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>which ſtands cloſe to God and his cauſe,
without fainting or giving over) ſhall inherit all things, and I will be
his God, and he ſhall be my ſonne. But, the fearefull and unbelievers</hi>
(ſee here, <hi>O cowardly Newters,</hi> to thy ſhame and terrour, who are put
in the very front or forlorne hope of the rabble of wicked ones, that
ſhall be ſhut out of the <hi>New-Jeruſalem) ſhall have their part in the
like which burnes with fire and brimſtone.</hi> Take heed therefore my
brethren (as the Authour to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> adviſeth) <hi>leſt there be in
any of you an evill heart of unbeliefe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 38.</note> 
                  <hi>in departing from the living
God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 9. 62.</note> For certainely, ſaies the ſpirit of truth (in the ſame Epiſtle)
<hi>If any man draw backe (or has, as Chriſt himſelfe teſtifies, put his
hand to the Plough of Gods worke and cauſe, and lookes backe, is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
for Heaven;</hi> nay more) <hi>Gods ſoule will take no pleaſure in ſuch an
one.</hi> Beſides, remember this ſeriouſly, I pray thee, that a <hi>Newter,</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:112665:20"/>
or Key-cold fellow in <hi>Gods cauſe,</hi> is a moſt deſpicable creature,
deſpiſed both of <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Devill,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The miſerable condition of Cowards and Newters de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</note> being apt to be falſe and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
to them both, and ſo good for the uſe of neither of them, as not
caring whether <hi>Gods</hi> or the <hi>Devils cauſe</hi> faile or prevaile, ſinke
or ſwim; what cares he ſo he may ſit ſtil and enjoy his baſe
peace and pelfe? onely, it may be, he will give them ſome ſeeming
good wiſhes, at moſt and beſt. O let ſuch as theſe, timely take
heed by theſe examples, that God meet them not ſorely and ſurely
too at laſt: and if thy <hi>Neutrality</hi> be from wilfull and wicked
principles, then feare indeed and tremble at thy eſtate, by thoſe
examples of <hi>Gods hand</hi> upon thoſe miſchievous and malevolent
<hi>malignants</hi> by death and deſtruction, even in the very acting of
their evils. If out of meere <hi>ſlaviſh feare</hi> and unworthy <hi>cowardiſe,</hi>
yet feare alſo by thoſe other examples, conſidering what terrible
ſtraits and ſoule-pinching perplexities it may bring thee unto, at
the beſt; and preſume not, though they happily repented and were
ſaved; for repentance is a Flower that growes not naturally in
our Gardens, but is the onely gift of God, and he gives it graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
when and to whom he will. Therefore, I ſay, preſume not
but feare; and whiles thou haſt yet ſpace, labour for grace, even
immoveable faithfulneſſe, courage, and perſeverance; remembring
ever, who it was that ſaid, even truth it ſelfe, <hi>He that denies me, or is
aſhamed of me before men, I will deny him and be aſhamed of him before
my Father which is in Heaven.</hi> And thus I have done with theſe.</p>
               <p>But now in the laſt place I deſire alſo to ſpeake a word or two
unto our moſt unhappy, miſerable, and marble-hearted <hi>malignants</hi>
(whom from my ſoule I pity and pray for, as my brethren in the
fleſh) implacable and inveterate haters of <hi>Holineſſe</hi> and of a pure
<hi>Reformation,</hi> who would faine (under a beggarly pretext of a
lazy, licentious <hi>Peace,</hi> forſooth) ſtill be more and more ſetled on
the Lees of their old, infant, halfe Reformation, (comfortable
then I confeſſe, in bleſſed Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> daies, if we reflect on
the wofull <hi>Marian</hi> daies before) even meere formall <hi>Protestan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme</hi>
at large, which in effect is but down-right <hi>Atheiſme;</hi> or at
beſt, a back doore to <hi>Papiſtry,</hi> as we have uſed the matter for ſo
many yeeres paſt; The upholding and maintaining whereof, I
take for granted; to be the ground of the great quarrell betweene
them and Gods people now adaies. What will ye (then) or
what can ye ſay for your ſelves poore mole-ey'd and miſerable
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:112665:21"/>
men? (after the ſerious fight and rumination on all theſe forelaid
remarkable evidences and moſt luculent and conſpicuous demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations
of <hi>Gods immediate hand both againſt and upon you;</hi> and
after all theſe notable <hi>Convictions</hi> and <hi>Confeſſions</hi> of the horrible
and God-hated <hi>evill</hi> of your <hi>cauſe</hi> and <hi>caſes;</hi>) what, I ſay, will
you now anſwer for your ſelves, why you may not moſt properly
and pertinently be called and counted <hi>wilfull and obſtinate fighters
againſt God and his juſt cauſe?</hi> See then, I beſeech you (but if you
will not timely ſee, you ſhall (as I ſaid before) ſee at laſt and be
aſhamed and ſmart too) and be timely and wiſely perſwaded (as
the truth is) that though you will not acknowledge it, you your
malignant workes plainely ſhew it, and eſpecially the Spirit of
God (the onely true ſearcher and diſcoverer of the hearts and
reines of all) hath moſt clearely declared to us in the ſecond
Pſalme, both your <hi>worke</hi> and your <hi>wages,</hi> your <hi>wicked cauſe;</hi> and
your <hi>wretched caſes,</hi> viz. That all the banding and binding of the
heads and hearts together of <hi>Gebal, Ammon</hi> and <hi>Amaleck</hi> &amp;c.
of ſottiſh <hi>formall Proteſtants,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">What King our formall Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants chooſe and refuſe.</note> 
                  <hi>Prelates</hi> and <hi>Papiſts,</hi> with all
that <hi>Ieſuiticall rabble,</hi> is mainely and onely this; <hi>We will not have
this man, King Ieſus;</hi> (but the tyrannicall and diabolicall <hi>uſurpers,</hi>
baſe <hi>luſts,</hi> ſoul-ſlaying <hi>corruptions, ſinne</hi> and <hi>Satan) to reigne over
us;</hi> and therefore let us (ſay they) breake his bands in ſunder; that
is, let us <hi>violate</hi> and <hi>vitiate</hi> his <hi>holy</hi> and <hi>wholſome</hi> Lawes and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements:
let us eaſt away his cords from us; that is, let us
contemne and deſpiſe his ſoul-ſaving counſels, free grace and love,
and all his heart-eſtabliſhing precious promiſes: but all this
while they blindly and blockiſhly forget, or will not ſee and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
(as the ſame <hi>Spirit</hi> and fountaine of <hi>Truth</hi> tels them) that the
Lord now reſolves to ſet his onely begotten Sonne <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> as
<hi>Lord and King</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and raigne (over the tops of all the <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines</hi>
of the earth) upon <hi>Sion</hi> his moſt holy <hi>Hill;</hi> and that he
therefore, even the <hi>Lord,</hi> the great <hi>Iehovah</hi> ſits in Heaven ſees, and
ſmiles at, and laughs to ſcorne all their combinations and accurſed
confederacies, all their freting and fuming, beating and breaking
of their braines and hearts too,<note place="margin">When Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants cauſe ſhal overcome.</note> and telling them to their teeth, and
ſhewing them, maugre their brazen browes, that all the while
<hi>they doe but imagine a vaine thing,</hi> which they never can they never
ſhall bring to paſſe; For of this let them be moſt ſure, that till they
can make it appeare or probable that <hi>Satan</hi> is ſtronger and wiſer
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:112665:21"/>
than the <hi>Almighty,</hi> that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is able to overcome the <hi>Lord
Chriſt,</hi> to whom the <hi>Father</hi> hath committed all power in Heaven
and Earth; I ſhall never believe, that <hi>they</hi> or their <hi>cauſe</hi> ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile.
For, I ſay, God hath put into Chriſts hands an <hi>Iron Mace,</hi>
not onely to <hi>bruiſe,</hi> but to <hi>breake in pieces</hi> (like ſo many <hi>pot-ſheards</hi>)
their earthen and ſtony hearts though ever ſo ſeemingly ſtout and
ſtubborne, as partly and pretty-well (one would thinke) I have
here, in theſe forecited examples made moſt plaine and conſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
but eſpecially, as the <hi>Lord God</hi> himſelfe in all ages and times
hath made moſt manifeſt to the whole World, even from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
of it to our preſent times;<note place="margin">Pſal. 76. 10.</note> nay, not onely ſo, but that the <hi>Lord
hath moſt admirably made</hi> (and that with a witneſſe too) <hi>the wrath
of man to turne to his own high glory and praiſe, yea and ſo reſtrained and
conſtrained the remainder thereof</hi> to keepe within limits and bounds,
as not to breake out to do that miſchiefe unto <hi>His</hi> which their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant
adverſaries moſt deſperately and divelliſhly intended to
have done unto them.<note place="margin">Malignants are but Gods drudges, and ſcull-boyes to his Church and children.</note> Nay (wherein they are yet farre more mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable,
yea moſt miſerable of all) God moſt wiſely and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
makes them in this their intended malice and miſchiefe, to be
but as it were, the very <hi>drudges</hi> and <hi>ſcull-boyes</hi> of his <hi>Church</hi> and
<hi>children<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and to doe them farre more good than hurt, in ſcouring
and refining them from their droſſe and filth contracted from the
rubbiſh of the world in this life; yea and by their <hi>malignant plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings,
fighting</hi> and <hi>ſpighting,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reverend and religious Mr. <hi>Marſhall.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>curſing, ſwearing, jeſting</hi> and <hi>jeering</hi> at
<hi>truth</hi> and <hi>holineſſe</hi>) they ſhall (as a moſt holy and reverend Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter
of the Lord, ſaid) exceedingly helpe forward, promote
and advance <hi>Gods cauſe,</hi> yea more (many times) than many of the
choice friends thereof; and yet (which, I ſay, is the <hi>height</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
the <hi>depth</hi> of their <hi>miſery</hi>) when they have thus done <hi>Gods
worke</hi> (though they little thought it, and never intended it) <hi>they
themſelves</hi> (like the blinde builders of <hi>Noahs Arke,</hi> who were
after it drowned in the <hi>Deluge</hi>) ſhall be ſo farre from having any
part or portion in the <hi>comfortable iſſue</hi> &amp; <hi>prosperity</hi> of his <hi>cauſe,</hi> that
they ſhal die in their ſinne, and be everlaſtlingly damned and periſh
for their paines therein; if, I ſay, in the interim<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God in his infinite
&amp; boundleſſe rich mercy, gives them not ſpace and grace to repent.</p>
               <p>What an unexpreſſible ſad condition are ye (then) in, O moſt
miſerable <hi>Malignants,</hi> if you could but ſee this your <hi>wicked
worke,</hi> and this your <hi>wretched wages,</hi> as aforeſaid, even with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:112665:22"/>
                  <hi>Eſau,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hebr. 12. 16. 1 King. 21. 20.</note> thus to ſtrive and ſtruggle to ſell away (as 'twas
ſaid of <hi>Ahab,</hi> that <hi>he ſold himſelfe to worke wickedneſſe</hi>) your
bleſſed <hi>Birth-right</hi> of life and ſalvation. (I ſpeake here the pure
language of <hi>Canaan,</hi> maugre the falſe and fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhie conceits and
whimſies of our impious <hi>Antinomians,</hi> thoſe ſlye and jugling un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derminers
of Chriſtian <hi>humiliation</hi> for ſinne,<note place="margin">A juſt objur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinomians, by way of a briefe digreſſion.</note> and of all other ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<hi>duties,</hi> under a colour of their either ignorant or perverſe wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
and miſapplying of <hi>Gods eternall decree of ſalvation</hi> and <hi>free
grace</hi> to his children. Yea, I ſay of thoſe unjuſt and injurious
ſcandalizers of our venerable, pious, and moſt painfull <hi>Paſtors,</hi>
falſly terming them <hi>Legall Preachers,</hi> and preſſers of performance
<hi>of holy duties in our owne ſtrength and abilities;</hi> a moſt groſſe ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall
and aſperſion audaciouſly caſt on them by theſe <hi>Satans Seedſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi>
of <hi>ſedition</hi> and <hi>diviſion</hi> in point of Religion. Pardon, good
Reader, this glancing digreſſion of zeale in me, and now to go on)
to ſtruggle, I ſay, with prophane <hi>Eſau,</hi> to ſell your bleſſed <hi>Birth-right</hi>
of <hi>life</hi> and <hi>ſalvation,</hi> for a poore, baſe, and beggarly <hi>morſell
of meat,</hi> or <hi>meſſe of pottage</hi> of worldly pel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, carnall pleaſure,
and pretended peace forſooth, which ſhall all periſh in the uſe of
them, and prove unto you nothing but meere vani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y and vexation
of ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Ceaſe then, I beſeech you, O moſt unholy and unhappy <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants,</hi>
ceaſe I ſay, and that timely too, thus to fret and fume, to
ſwear and ſwagger, and to ſhew your ſelves ſuch palpable and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent
<hi>fighters againſt God,</hi> ſuch banders and combiners againſt
Chriſt in his precious and peculiar members, whom though you
doe in your life and healthy times ſcorne and contemne,<note place="margin">The eſteeme that Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants have of Round-heads in the times of their ſickneſſe and diſtreſſes.</note> yet in
times of ſickneſſe or extreme ſtraits and heavy preſſures, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience-diſtreſſes,
theſe are the onely men you fare the better for;
theſe are the men, I ſay, that you are often enforced (even out of
Conſcience) to ſend for in your ſickneſſe (eſpecially when you
thinke 'tis a ſickneſſe to death) to pray for you, counſell and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
you; yea, and ofttimes in health too, are conſtrained to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
of them,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 24. 17.</note> and to ſay with wicked <hi>Saul</hi> to holy <hi>David, Thou
art more righteous than I, for thou haſt rewarded me good, whereas I
have rewarded thee evill.</hi> And therefore truly friends, in theſe like
caſes, I may greatly and moſt juſtly feare (and I beſeech you marke
well what I now ſhall ſay unto you, and feare and tremble at it
too) that moſt of the <hi>Grandees</hi> and <hi>Coſmopolites</hi> of theſe our abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minably
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:112665:22"/>
                  <hi>back ſliding</hi> and <hi>apoſtatizing times,</hi> (moſt of them, I ſay,
for I beleeve that they doe not <hi>all fight againſt God upon one and the
ſame principle</hi>) eſpecially our learned &amp; knowing <hi>Courtiers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Marke this, O our learned and knowing Malignants.</note> 
                  <hi>Prelates,
ſcandalous Prieſts,</hi> and intelligent <hi>Proteſtants at large,</hi> I greatly
feare, I ſay, that they come as neere to that ſinne, that terrible and
unpardonable <hi>ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt,</hi> and are as deeply plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
into it as ever any <hi>Apoſtate</hi> before them which ſinne, (if I
miſtake not) <hi>is wilfully,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt.</note> 
                  <hi>knowingly, maliciouſly, and perſeveringly to
perſecute and proſecute with all ſpight and bitterneſſe of ſpirit the Truth
and true Profeſſors thereof,</hi> eo nomine, <hi>becauſe it is, and they know
it is the Truth of God,</hi> and therefore they cannot abide it, becauſe
their owne workes being darkneſſe, they love darkneſſe more than
light.<note place="margin">2 Theſ 2. 10. 11, 12.</note> And that there are <hi>ſuch</hi> to be found, the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies,
and their deſperate <hi>condition</hi> too) and I make no doubt but
ſome of them have or will bee enforced ere they dye to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
and cry out,<note place="margin">I have credibly heard that a ſome of the Kings Cormo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants or Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers have in our late wars cryed out, Let us be gon, for God fights againſt us, as Serjeant-Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor-Generall <hi>Baſſet</hi> a Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſt, who at the diſſolution of the ſiege at <hi>Plimouth,</hi> ſpake the very words to one of our Commanders in our works at his going away.</note> if not true penitence, yet in damnable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire,
with that accurſed <hi>Apoſtate Julian</hi> the heatheniſh Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,
<hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iciſti Galilae, viciſti;</hi> So theſe, <hi>You have overcome us, O
Puritans and Round heads, you have overcome us;</hi> for Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
have overtaken us in contending againſt you. And therefore
I may and muſt ſay unto you all, who ever you be in this caſe,
and perſiſt therein, as <hi>Simon Peter</hi> ſaid to <hi>Simon Magnus, You are
certainly in the gall of bitterneſſe,</hi> in thus abuſing the Spirit of grace
and his peculiar and precious jewels; <hi>pray therefore, O yet pray, if
peradventure this ſinne may be forgiven you:</hi> which indeed is the
<hi>ultimum refugium,</hi> the laſt and beſt refuge and hope you have, yet
moſt unlikely to helpe you, if not ſerious and ſeaſonable; <hi>For, he
that turnes away his eare from hearing the Law</hi> (that is, <hi>from lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
God and goodneſſe, his Cauſe, his Saints and Servants) even his
very prayers are an abomination to the Lord.</hi> And then you may
with wicked <hi>Eſau</hi> begge the bleſſing you ſo careleſly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuouſly
ſold away, even with frightfull cryes and teares,
and yet everlaſtingly goe without it. <hi>O conſider this therefore, all
ye that thus forget God, leſt he ſuddenly teare you in pieces, and there
be none to deliver you.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 8. 23.</note> And ſince all theſe things are thus conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous
and evident by all thoſe remarkable forementioned and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited
examples,<note place="margin">Mal. 3. 17.</note> let not any of the <hi>Malignant</hi> fellow-factors of ſo
foule abuſes to <hi>Gods Cauſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 28. 9.</note> his Church and Children, wilfully
cloſe up the eyes of their uunderſtanding,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50. 22.</note> and ſtill harden their
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:112665:23"/>
hearts and ſpirits againſt ſuch providentiall workings and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrative
convictions and confeſſions as thoſe are, leſt they alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
fellow-ſeelers of the like exemplary and moſt juſt correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
But pray,<note place="margin">Revel. 3. 18.</note> O pray (as I will with you and for you) that <hi>God
would annoint your eyes with that Collyrium, his precious eye-ſalve, that
you may ſee;</hi> and that he would ſpeake to your Soules and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences
with a powerfull <hi>Ephphata,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark 7. 34.</note> 
                  <hi>Be ye opened;</hi> that ſo you might
ſee and repent. For I ingenuouſly confeſſe, that unleſſe his Spirit
ſpeakes thus, all the meanes in the world elſe that may be uſed come
too ſhort, and are but in vaine: yet give me leave to ſpeake unto
you as the Lord did to ſtubborne <hi>Iſrael</hi> by the Prophet,<note place="margin">Ezek. 3. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>You, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
you will heare or not heare (for you are a rebellious and obſtinate
people) yet ſhall you know that there hath been a word among you;</hi> that
the meanes have not beene wanting to you, and if you (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
all Threats and Treats, Mercies, or Judgements) will
perſiſt deſperately in your malignant folly &amp; madneſſe, I muſt and
will farther ſay unto you all, as the Spirit of God did of old <hi>Elies</hi>
moſt wicked and malignant two ſonnes,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 2. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>Notwithſtanding all that
their old godly father had ſaid unto them, they hearkned not to the voice
of their father, and why? becauſe (ſayes the Spirit of God) the Lord
had a purpoſe, for their incorrigible wickedneſſe, to ſtay and deſtroy them.</hi>
Wherefore to conclude all, my counſell (in briefe) ſhall be unto
you all,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2. 10, 11, 12.</note> poore miſerable <hi>malignant</hi> men and women, onely that of
the holy Spirit of God himſelfe by the holy Prophet <hi>David, Bee
wiſe now therefore, O ye malignant Princes and Peers of the earth: be
inſtructed and timely adviſed, O ye Judges and great Ones of the land.
Serve the Lord with feare, and rejoyce with trembling. Kiſſe the Son,
even the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, leſt he be angry, and ſo ye periſh from the
way, when his wrath is kindled, yea but a little: (O what will it be then
when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is mightily inflamed?) O then moſt bleſſed are all they only that put
their truſt in him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 4. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>and reſt under the ſhadow of his wings, where onely
is true healing for body and ſoule.</hi> The Lord give us all aſſiſting and
perſevering grace ſo to doe. Amen, and Amen.</p>
               <closer>Omnis gloria ſolius eſt Domini.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="epilogue">
               <pb facs="tcp:112665:23"/>
               <head>An Epilogue
TO MALIGNANTS,
In the Language of Canaan.</head>
               <p>IF now after the peruſall (if at leaſt thou hadſt any <hi>piety</hi>
or <hi>patience</hi> there unto) of all formerly ſaid and ſhewne
unto thee,<note place="margin">1. Malignants reſolution to God.</note> thou are yet refractorily reſolved to ſay, as
the <hi>Malignants</hi> did in <hi>Jeremiahs</hi> time to him:<note place="margin">Ier. 44. 16, 17.</note> 
                  <hi>As for the
words which thou haſt ſpoken to us in the name of the Lord, we
will not hearken unto thee, but we will certainly do whatſoever
thing commeth out of our owne mouth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then give me leave to tell thee the Lords reſolution
concerning thee.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Gods reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants.</note> Behold, I have ſworne by my great Name
(ſaith the Lord) that my name ſhall be no more named in the
mouth of any malignant.<note place="margin">Ier. 44. 26, 27.</note> Behold I will watch over them for
evill and not for good.<note place="margin">Iſa. 33. 10, 11.</note> Yea, now will I ariſe (ſaith the Lord)
now will I be exalted; now will I lift up my ſelfe; ye ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive
Chaffe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ye ſhall bring forth Stubble, your owne (curſing)
breath, as fire, ſhall devoure you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But, as for you my people, (my cordiall Covenanters,
yet that have ſinned againſt me) for your ſins,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3. Gods reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</note> I will cauſe
you to paſſe under the rod; I will bring you into the bond of the
Covenant or Holy-league;<note place="margin">Ezek. 20, 37, 38.</note> And then I will purge out from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
you the Rebels or Malignants, and them that tranſgreſſe
againſt me. I will bring them out of the Countrey where they
ſojourne, and they ſhall not enter into the Land of Iſrael, or hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe
of my children.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
